<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The case stated of the jurisdiction of the House of Lords in the point of impositions</title>
            <author>Holles, Denzil Holles, Baron, 1599-1680.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1676</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 124 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 59 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A44185</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing H2453</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R20018</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12561827</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12561827</idno>
            <idno type="VID">63248</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A44185)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 63248)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 961:23)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The case stated of the jurisdiction of the House of Lords in the point of impositions</title>
                  <author>Holles, Denzil Holles, Baron, 1599-1680.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>114 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1676.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Cambridge University Library.</note>
                  <note>Errata: p. 114.</note>
                  <note>Attributed to Denzil Holles. cf. NUC pre-1956.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>England and Wales. --  Parliament. --  House of Lords.</term>
               <term>Taxation --  England.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2008-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-01</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-03</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-03</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:63248:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:63248:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE Caſe ſtated OF THE JURISDICTION OF THE Houſe of <hi>LORDS</hi> In the point of IMPOSITIONS.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed in the Year 1676.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:63248:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:63248:2"/>
            <head>The Caſe ſtated of the Juriſdi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of the Houſe of Lords in the point of Impoſitions.</head>
            <p>As the Lords are of nothing more deſirous, than of keeping a good correſpondence with the Houſe of Commons, ſo are they, and have ever been moſt careful to take nothing from the Houſe of Commons, which belongs unto them, nor to aſſume any thing to themſelves, but what hath ever been their undoubted right, and never ſo much as queſtioned to their Anceſtors in any preceding Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
            <p>And to have the free uſe of their reaſon, to diſapprove and diſallow all or any part of any thing propounded unto them for the Publick Service, which they in their Judgments believe not to be conducing to it, or ſo to alter and amend it as to make it ſuch,
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:63248:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>is ſo proper, ſo eſſential, ſo neceſſary to the conſtitution of the Houſe of Lords, as they do not think they are a Houſe of Parliament, or can act as a Houſe of Parliament if this be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyed them.</p>
            <p>Now they conceive the point in queſtion betweene them and the Houſe of Commons, to be of this very nature. The Houſe of Commons ſent up a Bill to them to lay Rates and Impoſitions upon ſeveral ſorts of Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chandize. The Merchants Petition the Lords againſt many particulars in that Bill, ſhew the inequality and diſproportion of the Rates impoſed upon certain Commodities to be ſuch, as if not altered, and ſome which were to high, brought down to hold a true proportion with others, which the Houſe of Commons had ſet low, it would have utterly ruined the whole Trade of thoſe Commodities, and have brought an irreparable pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judice upon all our Plantations, and conſequently upon the whole King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom; that of thoſe Commodities be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the principal Trade of the
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:63248:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>Plantations, and that of the Planta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of moſt conſiderable part of the Trade of the Kingdom.</p>
            <p>The Lords were ſo fully convinced with the arguments and demonſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of the Merchants, and thereupon judged it of ſuch abſolute neceſſity to make ſome alterations in the Bill, and to lower ſome of thoſe rates, that they did ſo: and the Bill ſo altered and amended they returned to the Houſe of Commons, giving withall their rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons for thoſe Amendments and Alte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations, which was done at a Confe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence.</p>
            <p>The Houſe of Commons took this ill, and preſently paſſed a Vote, <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claring it to be a fundamental right lodged in their Houſe alone, to impoſe Rates upon Merchandize, as to Matter, Meaſure, and Time, and to paſs Bills for that purpoſe, and this in excluſion of the Houſe of Lords.</hi> Which Reſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution of theirs was by them delivered back at a Conference, and withal ſome particular reaſons given to juſtifie their Rates Impoſed in oppoſition to the alterations made by the Lords:
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:63248:4"/>But the maine Objection, which they ſtill urged, and with which they clo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed every Period of their Diſcourſe was, <hi>That the Lords had nothing to do with the altering of any Rate impoſed by them upon Merchandize.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Lords eaſily apprehended the ill conſequence of ſuch a Maxim, how it did ſhake the very foundation of Parliament, and utterly over-throw the Being of their Houſe, rendring it altogether uſeleſſe to the general good of the Nation: Becauſe it could then contribute nothing to what is of ſo great conſequence to it, as is the car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rying on of Trade, and the juſt bal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lancing of it, if ſo be any ſlip or mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtake, or error ſhould happen to have been in what had paſſed to that pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe in the Houſe of Commons, (as no Society of men but may erre) And therein conſiſts the excellency of the conſtitution of our Government, that every Law hath firſt in each Houſe of Parliament three Examens, like ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny paſſings through the fire, to refine and purifie it. And that done in one Houſe, then the other Houſe takes it,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:63248:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>and examines it over again in like manner three ſeveral times: And if any droſs remain, or any thing be yet wanting to make it better and fitter to paſs, care is there taken to do all that is further needful; ſo one Houſe is both a Check and a help to the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, which is the great ſecurity of the Kingdom. This the Lords ſaw muſt inevitably ceaſe. And therefore they judged it, to be of abſolute pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent neceſſity, in the firſt place to make that ſure, and aſſert a Priviledg ſo undoubtedly theirs, and indiſpenſably neceſſary for the good of the Publick, of King, People and Parliament; which they did by a Vote. <hi>That the power exerciſed by the Houſe of Peers in making the Amendments and Abate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments in that Bill, was a Fundamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal, inherent and undoubted right of the Houſe of Peers, from which they could not depart.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This Vote backt with many Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, and confirmed by Preſidents, they communicate to the Houſe of Commons likewiſe at a Conference, which yet did not ſatisfie, as appeared
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:63248:5"/>by what was delivered by them at an other Conference, which preſently followed; For they begin with telling the Lords, <hi>That three things did ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prize the Commons at the former Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference:</hi> 1ſt. <hi>That expecting a diſcourſe upon the Amendments of the Bill, they met with nothing but a debate for the Liberties of their Houſe, and a demand of the delivering up of thoſe Liberties by a Publick acknowledgment, before any further diſcourſe upon the Bill.</hi> 2dly. <hi>That their Lordſhips ſhould de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare ſo fixed a reſolution before hearing what could be replyed by the Commons.</hi> 3dly. <hi>That their Lordſhips ſhould be ſo eaſily induced to take up that Reſolution, if they have no other motive, than the Reaſons and Preſidents which they had produced.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But why they ſhould be ſo ſurprized with theſe three things, is not eaſie to be imagined: For certainly no man ought to be ſurprized with what he might rationally expect. And firſt, that the Lords ſhould trouble themſelves to anſwer particular Objections to particular points, before they had
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:63248:5"/>removed one main one, which alone took off all poſſibility of Agreement, and was by the Commons generally applyed and preſſed by them upon every point, as it had been a very fruitleſs labour of their Lordſhips, ſo it could not be with any reaſon expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted from them.</p>
            <p>And as little reaſon had they to be ſurprized with the ſecond thing, for nothing is more ordinary in the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings of both Houſes, than to be moſt jealous of their Priviledges, not to ſuffer them ſo much as to be diſpu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, but upon the leaſt attempt againſt them, preſently to aſſert them with vehemence. The Houſe of Commons themſelves gave an example of it, in this very buſineſs but at the foregoing Conference, when upon the Lords making an abatement in theſe Rates, they preſently come and tell them, <hi>That the queſtion being concerning Rates and Impoſitions upon Merchan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dize, there is in this a Fundamental right in the Houſe of Commons, both as to the Matter, and the Meaſure, and the Time unalterable, and which they
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:63248:6"/>not part with.</hi> Here was a Reſolution fixed, and ſetled ſufficiently, and without hearing what the Lords could ſay againſt it: And why then ſhould it ſeem ſo ſtrange that the Lords ſhould be as reſolute in the aſſerting of their Right?</p>
            <p>Their third ſurprize, (one may ſay) is a piece of Sophiſtry; for ſince they cannot anſwer the Reaſons alledged by the Lords in the maintenance of their Aſſertion, nor diſprove their Preſidents, they would ſeem to ſlight them, and wonder their Lordſhips ſhould be ſo eaſily perſwaded by them, having no other Motives.</p>
            <p>In the next place they would per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade the Lords, that in their Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidents there is a departure from the queſtion, which is only concerning power of Abatement of Impoſitions upon Merchandize; whereas theſe Preſidents go to a joint power of im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſing and beginning of Taxes, which (ſay they)the Lords do not pretend to.</p>
            <p>Nor indeed do they pretend to it, neither did they cite thoſe Preſidents for that purpoſe. And the Houſe of
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:63248:6"/>Commons ſhould not put upon them any other or further conſtruction, than they were produced for. This may pre-poſſeſs ſtanders by with a preju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dice, as if the Lords would aſſume to themſelves a power of laying a charge upon the Nation at their pleaſure; but is not the way to diſcover, who is in the right for his preſent preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions. This is cleer; They do prove that in thoſe times, the Lords and the Commons did joyn in the gift, that the one could not give without the other, except they had otherwiſe agreed it among themſelves, and that they would give ſeparately, as they have ſometimes done, and but rarely. Four times in <hi>Edward</hi> the thirds Reign, 13 <hi>E.</hi> 3. n. 7, 8. &amp; 18 <hi>E.</hi> 3. n: 10. &amp; 20 <hi>E.</hi> 3. n. 11. &amp; 27 <hi>E.</hi> 3. n. 8. once in <hi>E.</hi> 4ths time. 12 <hi>E</hi> 4. n. 8, 9. and in the 29th <hi>Eliz.</hi> the Commons having made humble ſuit to the Lords to joyn with them in a Contribution or Benevolence to the Queen: The Lords gave anſwer, that they would leave the Commons to themſelves, and they would rate themſelves, which
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:63248:7"/>they did at 2 <abbr>
                  <hi>s.</hi>
               </abbr> in the pound, after the rate of the valuation of the Subſidy.</p>
            <p>But the ordinary way of Parliament, hath ever been for the two Houſes to joyn in the gift. And this not to be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood by a figure of <hi>Reddendo ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gula ſingulis</hi> (as was ſaid at the Confe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence by him that managed it for the Houſe of Commons), as if the Lords gave one part, and the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons another part, and the Lords to have nothing to do with what the Commons give, and the Commons nothing to do with what the Lords give: And though they ſay, We Lords and Commons grant to your Majeſty this and this, and here we both of us joyntly make to your Majeſty one Preſent, and give you one gift, we tell you ſo, yet it is not ſo, but your Majeſtly muſt <hi>Reddere ſingula ſingulis,</hi> and take one part of it as coming from your Lords, and the other part as coming from your Commons: And though your Majeſty doth graciouſly return one thanks to us both, yet we ſhall likewiſe <hi>Reddere ſingula ſingulis,</hi> and divide the thanks between us,
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:63248:7"/>and take each of us his part. Is this a Parliament ſtile? are Laws penned in ſuch Ambiguous and ſenſe-confound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing terms? doth an Act of Parliament ſay, that the Lords and Commons grant a whole Subſidy to the King, when neither of them doth ſo, and each of them hath nothing to do with ſome part of the grant? No certainly: Acts of Parliaments, and Laws, ſpeak diſtinctly, and their expreſſions are always litterally true: And where they ſay the Lords and Commons grant, both have an intereſt, and both exerciſe a power in granting.</p>
            <p>Beſides, in a Subſidy of Tunnage and Poundage, in which only Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chants and Tradeſmen are concerned, what ſingularity can be pretended of any thing belonging peculiarly to the Lords, that they ſhould be ſaid to give there but for themſelves, and not to be at all concerned in what is done, as to the generality of the Kingdom? Therefore, if they joyn there in grant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, it muſt be in reference to others, and not to themſelves, and peruſe all the Records, from the 17th of <hi>R.</hi> 2. n. 12.
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:63248:8"/>upwards to the very firſt Subſidies of that nature given by Parliament, it will be found, that the ſtile was con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantly, <hi>We the Lords and Commons do grant, &amp;c.</hi> And though ſince it hath ſometimes varied in form, the ſenſe hath ſtill been one and the ſame. For if it was true then, that the Lords had a part in the giving, as the words all along are plain they had, they muſt have a part ſtill, having never quitted it by their own Act, nor loſt it by the Act of any other. The Figure then of <hi>Redddendo fingula ſingulis</hi> mends not the matter; yet ſome alteration hath been, as hereafter will be ſhewed, though not in the giving part, and that by which it comes to be a gift to the King.</p>
            <p>But then, ſaith the Manager of that Conference for the Houſe of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons: <hi>If it be not ſo to be underſtood, then to Grant ſignifies only to Aſſent, and to ſay the Lords grant, is as much as to ſay, the Lords Aſſent to what the Commons grant.</hi> But will this Expoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion hold? Can it be ſaid, that to give, is to be content another ſhall give? If
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:63248:8"/>this be giving, one may find givers enough, and a man may be cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritable upon eaſie terms: Would any man (think we) be content, if ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther and he were bound to give ſuch a man a hundred pounds, if he who were to give part of the Mony with him, as being together bound, ſhould ſay, I am bound only to conſent that you ſhould give it all, not to give any my ſelf: I believe if the Manager of the Conference were the man to whom it ſhould be ſo ſaid, he would then expound it otherwiſe, and ſay to his fellow-Obligee, that to give and grant is one thing, and to give con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent another ſhall give and grant, is another thing, and you are bound Sir to give as well as I, and not to be willing only that I ſhould give all: And by the ſame Grammar he might conclude, that where it is ſaid, <hi>That the Lords and Commons do give and grant ſo and ſo to the King,</hi> the meaning is, That it is a Grant of the Lords, as well as of the Commons, and the Lords do give as well as the Commons; and certainly in good Engliſh it can have no other conſtruction.</p>
            <pb n="14" facs="tcp:63248:9"/>
            <p>But then he will tell you, that there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the ſtile was altered afterwards, and to declare the gift to come only from the Commons, it ran thus: <hi>We the Commons by advice and conſent of the Lords Spiritual and Temporal, do give and grant, &amp;c.</hi> Well, admit that to be now the ſetled conſtant form and not to be altered, which yet we know is not ſo; for ſometimes the ancient form hath been obſerved in explicit terms, <hi>We the Lords and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons, &amp;c.</hi> Sometimes implicitly, <hi>We your Loyal Subjects do give and grant, &amp;c.</hi> But be it, <hi>The Commons with the Aſſent of the Lords, do give, &amp;c.</hi> It doth not at all follow, but that the Lords have ſtill power to alter and qualifie the gift, before they will aſſent to it.</p>
            <p>Nay, if it be ſo, that they muſt aſſent to it before the Houſe of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons can give it, (as that will not be denyed) it doth then neceſſarily fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low, that if it be not ſuch, as they can approve of in their Judgments, when it comes from the Houſe of Commons to them, they muſt have
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:63248:9"/>power to alter it, and make it ſuch, as that they may aſſent to it, except they muſt be denyed the uſe of their rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon; which would be a ſevere impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing upon a Houſe of Parliament, and an abſurd one: A Councel not to be ſuffered to debate and conſider of what is propoſed to it, and what ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice it ſhall give to him, who hath called it for that purpoſe to receive its advice; and ſo to frame it and mould it, as that it may be fit to be adviſed, This is to make a Councel to be no Councel, it is what the Logicians call <hi>Contradictio in adjecto,</hi> a quality in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſiſting with the Subject; as an Ora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor to be dumb, an Auditor to be deaf, a Watchman to be blind; ſo a Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cel to be without power to conſider, debate and ſatisfie it ſelf of the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſel that it muſt give. And it is directly contrary to the Writ which convenes and conſtitutes the Parliament. The Lords are ſummoned by it, <hi>Ad tractan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum &amp; conſilium impendendum de re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus arduis;</hi> but they muſt ſit there as ſo many Pariſh Clerks, only to ſay Amen to what the Houſe of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:63248:10"/>hath reſolved, and neither <hi>tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctare</hi> nor <hi>conſilium impendere.</hi> And what a Pageantry were this? to read a Bill of Subſidy ſolemnly, once, twice, thrice, commit it, perhaps to a Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mittee of the whole Houſe, make a great buſineſs, and when all is done, after all this ſtir, they muſt aſſent to it, and paſs it juſt as it came at firſt from the Houſe of Commons, be the miſtakes in it never ſo great, and the ill conſequences of it never ſo rui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nous.</p>
            <p>Can a rational man believe that a Houſe of Parliament ſhould be ſo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtituted, to act againſt the nature of a Parliament? Yes, will they ſay, for both Houſes do the ſame in ſome ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes; They can alter nothing in the Subſidy of the Clergy, nor in an Act for a General Pardon, and yet they give their Aſſents to paſs them for Laws: Which is very true, but makes nothing to this Caſe; for thoſe are things Eccentrick to Parliament, they have their motion in an other Sphere: The Convocation gives the one, The King of his free Grace beſtows the
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:63248:10"/>other; the Parliament only gives them the force of a Law, and may chuſe whether or no it will do that, when they are prepared to their hands; but it cannot meddle with the things themſelves, to make them this way or that way: But now what is ſaid here, is to be underſtood of things properly within the cognizance of the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and that receive their riſe and progreſs there, that is to ſay, in one of the two Houſes, (for the two Hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes make up but one Parliament.) And of ſuch things, where either Houſe is to give an aſſent to them, that Houſe may debate them, and alter and change them as it thinks good: And it mends not the matter to ſay, That Houſe may reject all, as the King may any Bill preſented to him, which hath paſſed both Houſes; For by the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution of the Government, the King hath only a Negative voice, but by the ſame conſtitution of Government the Parliament (that is, either Houſe in its Legiſlative capacity) hath not only a Negative, but alſo a Delibera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive voice in all things of which it is
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:63248:11"/>cognizable: And of nothing is it more cognizable, than of what concerns Trade, which is the wealth and ſtrength and ſupport of the Kingdom, for which concernments they are principally called, and ſummoned by the King's Writ.</p>
            <p>But how this particular of Trade, and Impoſitions upon Merchandize for the guarding of the Seas, and ſecuring Merchants Ships in their paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage out and home, for carrying on of Trade, came to be lodged in the care and power of the Parliament, and in what manner that power and care was firſt executed by them, (which was then equally in both Houſes to begin and propoſe what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever either Houſe thought fit) and how afterwards it came to be appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priated to the Houſe of Commons to be the firſt movers in thoſe Impoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and the Houſe of Lords to reſerve to themſelves only a power to qualifie and moderate the Sums im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed, and bring them to that due meaſure and proportion, which would be moſt convenient and advantageous
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:63248:11"/>to the Trade of the Kingdom, and if any error had ſlipped in at the firſt framing and compoſing of a Bill paſſed for that purpoſe in the Houſe of Commons, the Lords to reform and amend it; This, we ſay, is well worth the inquiry.</p>
            <p>It appears by the Records, that it was at firſt a meer act of State, the King with the advice of his great Councel the Spiritual and Temporal Lords contracting with Merchants, that they paying a certain rate for their Commodities whether exported or imported, he would undertake to waft over their Ships, and ſecure them from danger in their paſſage: Such was that agreement recited in the Patent Roll of 3 <hi>E.</hi> 1. m. 1. n. 1. which by him that managed the Confe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence for the Houſe of Commons, was much miſtaken; firſt upon point of Grammar, the words of it he ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledges to be as we ſay, that <hi>Magnates &amp; Communitas conceſſerunt;</hi> But <hi>Conceſſerunt</hi> he will have to relate only to <hi>Communitas,</hi> which is certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly falſe Grammar, and then <hi>Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitas</hi>
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:63248:12"/>he expounds to be the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons, which is a miſtake in the matter and true ſence of the Record: As for his Grammatical miſtake in the <hi>Syntaxis,</hi> and his ſo conſtruing the Record, he muſt give us leave to ſay, that he goes contrary to an univerſal known Rule in the Syntaxis of all Languages, that ever were yet ſpoken, which is this, That where there are ſeveral Nominative Caſes joyned together with a Conjunction copulative, they all do equally relate to the Verbe; ſo <hi>Magnates</hi> here muſt have the ſame influence upon the Verbe <hi>Conceſſerunt</hi> as <hi>Communitas,</hi> and they do alike <hi>Concedere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But then what will be ſaid, if <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munitas</hi> in that Record be not the Commons, as is ſurmiſed, but <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munitas Mercatorum</hi> the Community of Merchants, which any body would have ſeen, who had conſulted the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord, and not relyed wholly upon Sir <hi>Edward Cooke</hi>'s miſreciting it in Print, in thoſe two mentioned places,
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:63248:12"/>the 2d. part of the Inſtitutes, <hi>p.</hi> 531. and the 4th part, <hi>p.</hi> 29. But to give a true account of the marter: There are two Records of this, one in the Patent Roll, 3 <hi>E.</hi> 1. m. 1. n. 1. in La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tin, which is ſomething defaced, yet ſo much of it legible, as to ſerve for the diſproving of Sir <hi>Edward Cooke</hi>'s allegation, and the Comment now made upon it; for it runs thus, <hi>Rex omnibus, &amp;c. cum Praelati, &amp; Mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nates ac tota Communitas Mercatorum Regni noſtri nobis conceſſerint quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam</hi> —torn out,—<hi>coriis tam in Anglia, &amp;c. in forma ſubſcripta, vide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licet de quolibet</hi>—torn out,—<hi>pellibus quae faciunt unum ſaccum dimid' Marc' de qualibet leſta coriorum unam Marc', &amp;c.</hi> Then perſons are ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed to collect this duty; which is the ſum of that Record: And this is againe Regiſtred in <hi>Rotulo Finium,</hi> 3 <hi>E.</hi> 1. m. 24. tit, <hi>de nova Cuſtuma</hi> in French, viz. <hi>A la nouuelle Cuſtume ke eſt graunte par tout les Graunt del Reaume, e par la priere des Communes
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:63248:13"/>des Merchaunt de tut' Engleterre, &amp;c.</hi> And ſo goes on to tell what it is they grant <hi>de cheſcum ſac de leyne demi mark et de cheſcum treiſcent de peaus ke funt vn ſac demi mark de cheſcun laſte de kevir vn mark,</hi> and then takes courſe for the collecting, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> This Record is perfect, from the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning to the end, which any man may reſort to when he pleaſes, to ſatisfie himſelf, and the Houſe of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons, that here was no gift of the Commons in Parliament, but a pure contract of the Commonalty of Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chants with the King and Lords; which way of impoſing this duty at laſt came to be grievous, and the Parliament made great complaints of it ſeveral times.</p>
            <p>In the 21. of <hi>E.</hi> 3. at a great Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cel held in the King's abſence by <hi>Lio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nel</hi> of <hi>Antmerp,</hi> (as the Record ſtiles him) the King's Son, where there was no Houſe of Commons) there had been granted 2 <abbr>
                  <hi>s.</hi>
               </abbr> upon every Sack of Wool, 2 <abbr>
                  <hi>s.</hi>
               </abbr> upon every Tun of Wine, and 6 <abbr>
                  <hi>d.</hi>
               </abbr> in the pound upon all Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chandize for the payments of Ships
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:63248:13"/>to guard the Seas, and to Convoy Merchants, and this duty to continue till the <hi>Michaelmas</hi> following: The <hi>January</hi> after that, a Parliament was called, at which the Commons com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plained, that the payment upon the Wool (which ſhould have ended at <hi>Michaelmas</hi>) was ſtill demanded; and they deſire the King to forbid his Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficers the demanding of it any longer. The anſwer is, <hi>That that payment was prolonged until</hi> Eaſter, <hi>becauſe the King had been at great charge in ſetting out Ships, and was not yet reimburſed his money, which being for ſo ſhort a time ſhould not ſeem to be grievous,</hi> 21 <hi>E.</hi> 3. n. 11. And they complain again in the 25th <hi>E.</hi> 3. n. 11. of ſuch Impoſitions, which had been laid on a-new by an Agreement with the Merchants, and pray they may ceaſe, the Anſwer is, <hi>Le Roy S'auiſera et ſurceo les reſpondra en conuenable manere.</hi> Then in the 51th E. 3. n. 25. They come with a general deſire, that for the time to come the Prelates, Earls, Barons, Commons, Citizens, and Burgeſſes of the Kingdom may not
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:63248:14"/>be charged, moleſted nor grieved. <hi>De Commune aide faire</hi> or <hi>Charge ſuſtenir,</hi> by granting a common Aid, or bearing any charge, except by the common aſſent of the Prelates, Earls, Barons, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and this in full Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. They deſire alſo that no Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitions be laid upon Wool, and Wool fells, ſave the ancient one, of half a mark upon a Sack, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> To the firſt is anſwered, <hi>Le Roy neſt mie en volontee de le faire ſans grande neceſceite, et pur la defens du Roialme, et la ou il le purra faire par reſon;</hi> and for the other point of the Wools, The anſwer is, <hi>That there is a Statute in the caſe which the King wills to be in force:</hi> So here is a diſavowing of the thing, yet with a reſerve upon urgent neceſſity: though in the 14th. of his Reign, he had conſented to a Law, upon occaſion of a Grant made to him of the ninth Sheaf and Fleece, and Lamb; wherein he declares, that willing to provide for the Indempnity of the Prelates, Earls, Barons, and Commons, the ſame Grant ſhall not be had in Example another time, nor
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:63248:14"/>turn to their prejudice in time to come, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Further enacts, <hi>That they ſhall not from henceforth be charged, nor grieved to make any aid, or to ſuſtain charge, if it be not by the Common Aſſent of the Prelates, Earls, Barons, and other great men, and Commons of the Realm of</hi> England, <hi>and that in the Parliament,</hi> which are the words of the Statute, <hi>C.</hi> 1. of the ſecond Statutes made that year: The ſame in effect that he had bound him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf to by a former Act, made in the preceding Parliament of the ſame year, <hi>C.</hi> 21. when a Subſidy had been granted to him of Wool, Leather, and other Merchandizes that paſſed the Sea between <hi>Eaſter</hi> and <hi>Pentecoſt, That he nor his Heirs would for the fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture take more than the old Cuſtom.</hi> And in the 13th of his Reign part 1. n. 13. when he had by his own authority laid a charge upon Wool and Lead, the Commons come and pray it may be taken off, and that the Male-tot upon thoſe Commodities may be ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken as anciently it was accuſtomed, and not as then enhanſed without
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:63248:15"/>their aſſent, or of the Lords, <hi>Deſicome ele eſt enhancee ſaunz aſſent de la Commune ou des Grands,</hi> ſaith the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord: Where is to be noted by the way, that the Houſe of Commons then did not think, that the Lords were to be wholly excluded their Votes in thoſe Impoſitions, when they made it a ground of their exception, that they had not agreed to them.</p>
            <p>Certain it is, that though this King ſtruggled all his time with his Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments about the exerciſe of this power, and ſometimes did ſeem to yield, and would promiſe fair, at other times would deny any condeſcenſion to their deſires of being eaſed of thoſe Impoſitions, even when they com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plained, that notwithſtanding thoſe allowances and payments for guarding the Seas, and ſecuring Merchants, yet Merchants were robbed, and the Seas unguarded, as is ſet forth 21 E. 3. n. 58. yet ſtill the Parliament got ſome ground, and leſs and leſs was it practiſed in that Prerogative way: And after his time it was wholly remitted: and left to the Parliament,
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:63248:15"/>and there was not the leaſt attempt of reaſſuming it any more.</p>
            <p>But ever after it was taken by the King as a pure gift of the Parliament, of which the ſtile was, <hi>Wee the Lords and Commons doe give and grant, &amp;c.</hi> And the firſt variation of it was in the 21th of <hi>R. 2d.</hi> when it was, <hi>Wee the Commons with the aſſent of the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops and Lords, do give, &amp;c.</hi> which continued ſo for three or four Kings Reigns, and ſince hath been various, ſometimes as anciently, <hi>Wee the Lords and Commons,</hi> ſometimes without ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifying either, <hi>Wee your Loyal Subjects,</hi> and all ſignifying the ſame thing: That both joyned in the gift, as hath been already ſhewn. And ſo jealous were they of having it thought other than a pure gift of theirs, that they would ſometimes grant this Subſidy with a ſhort intermiſſion of time, in which the King ſhould not receive it, as 5 <hi>R.</hi> 2. n. 40. there was to be an inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption to the Kings taking of it for a week, between the Nativity and the Circumciſion: And the like 9 <hi>K.</hi> 2. n. 11. for above a moneth, from
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:63248:16"/>Midſummer to the firſt of <hi>Auguſt;</hi> and then 13 <hi>H.</hi> 4. n. 10. they ſpeak out and ſay they give it the King for a year, ſo always as the ſame ſhould be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed to proceed of their own good will, and not duty.</p>
            <p>27 E. 3. n. 9. Sir <hi>Bartholomew Burg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herſh,</hi> the Kings Chamberlain, made a long Speech to both Houſes, the King preſent, declaring the wrong which the King received from his Enemy of <hi>France</hi> (as the Record ſtiles him) keeping from him that Crown which was his right, that the King was re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved to recover it by force, and therefore deſired the Prelates, Lords and Commons to grant unto him the Subſidy of Wools, Wool-fells, and Leather, (which was then expired) for a longer time, <hi>Sur queu priere</hi> (ſaith the Record) <hi>eue deliberation entre les ditz Prelatz Grauntz et Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>es ſaſſenterent vnement et grante<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent au Roi le Subſide des Leyns Quirs et Peaux lanuz pur trois anz, &amp;c. Et que les deniers ſourdans de meſme le Subſide ſoient ſauuement gardez pur la dite guerre, ſans ceo qils ſoient mis
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:63248:16"/>en autre oeps, Dequent Grante noſtre S le Roi enmerciales Seigneurs et Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munes.</hi> The King here makes it his deſire to the Lords as well as to the Commons to grant it, They confer about it with the Commons, and to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether with them do grant it, then appoint how it ſhall be employed, on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to the War and to no other uſe, and afterwards receive the Kings thanks for their granting it, as well as the Commons: How then can it be ſaid, that the Lords muſt have nothing to do with theſe Grants?</p>
            <p>But then will it not be inferred, that if it be as much in the gift of the Lords as of the Commons, the Lords may not only moderate and abate, but alſo augment the gift, and propoſe it firſt in their Houſe, and give away the Peoples money at their pleaſure? It was certainly ſo in the beginning, but now not at all ſo, as the ſaying is, <hi>Modus &amp; Conventio vincunt legem,</hi> Agreement alters right. And though the certain time when this Agreement was firſt made, and when this was firſt altered, and all the circumſtances of
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:63248:17"/>that firſt Alteration, and of that A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greement cannot be made out by the Records yet it may be made out, that it was before the 9th of <hi>H.</hi> 4. n. 21, 22. when the Indempnity of the Lords and Commons (and of the Lords aſwel as of the Commons) was declared and ſetled by a Law made that Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment for that purpoſe, and the Law hath that title <hi>Indempnitee des Seig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neurs et Communes,</hi> and is abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dantly ſufficient to ſettle and eſtabliſh the manner of granting Subſidies in Parliament, and the power of pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding of either Houſe in paſſing Acts of that nature, were there nothing elſe. The Record ſets forth, That the King coming to the Lords Houſe in the Abbey at <hi>Gloceſter,</hi> and communication there had of the ſtate of the Kingdom then envi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roned with Enemies, and how be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hooveful it was to give a notable aid to the King, to enable him to reſiſt thoſe Enemies, the Lords being de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded what aid, did ſeverally give their opinions, <hi>That leſs would not ſerve then a tenth and half of the Cities
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:63248:17"/>and Burroughs, and a fifteenth and half of the reſt of the Laity, and to continue for two years the Subſidy of Wools, Wool fells and Leather, and the 3<abbr>d.</abbr> Tunnage, and poundage for other Commodities,</hi> which the King commanded ſhould be ſignified to the Houſe of Commons. And a meſſage was thereupon ſent to them, that they ſhould ſend up ſome of their number to heare what from the King would be ſaid unto them: Who ſent up a dozen of their Members, and to them was declared what had been moved to the Lords, and what their Lordſhips had anſwered, which they were willed to report to their Houſe, that ſo they might come to a conformity with the ſence of the Lords. The report be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing made to the Commons, <hi>Ils ent furent</hi> (ſaith the Record) <hi>grandement deſtourbez en diſant et affermant ce eſtre en grant prejudice, et derogation de lour libertees,</hi> they were greatly diſturbed, ſaying and affirming, that this was a great prejudice and dero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation to their liberties; which re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſented to the King, and he not
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:63248:18"/>willing that any thing ſhould be done, that might at preſent, or in after times turn to the prejudice of their Liberties, <hi>N'encontre les libertees de les ſeigneurs ſuſdits,</hi> nor againſt the liberty and freedom of the foreſaid Lords, Wills, Grants, and Declares with the advice and conſent of the Lords themſelves, That in this and all future Parliaments it ſhall be lawful for the Lords to debate and commune among themſelves of the State of the Kingdom, and the neceſſary reme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies: And likewiſe the Commons to do the ſame by themſelves: And that neither the Lords nor the Commons ſhall acquaint the King with any Grant made by the Commons, and by the Lords aſſented unto, nor with any of the Communications concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that Grant, till the Lords and Commons themſelves come to an Agreement and accord in that behalf, and then to be in the manner and form as hath been accuſtomed, that is to ſay, by the mouth of the Speaker of the Houſe of Commons for the time being, <hi>To the end that they the
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:63248:18"/>Lords and Commons may receive their thanks from our Lord the King.</hi> It being moreover the will of the King by the aſſent of the ſaid Lords, that the foreſaid Communication of this preſent Parliament, ſhall not be drawn into Example for the time to come, nor be made uſe of, neither in this nor in any future Parliament, to the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judice or derogation of the liberty of the State: Then, n. 23. is added, How the laſt day of the Parliament, the Speaker of the Houſe of Commons made it his prayer to the King, that he would grant unto that Houſe leave to depart in as much freedome, as o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers had formerly done, The King anſwers, That it pleaſed him well; and that he had alwayes been of that mind.</p>
            <p>Upon this memorable Record wee may make many Obſervations, and from them draw ſeveral Concluſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. As,
<list>
                  <item>1. That it was even before that time held to be againſt the Priviledge of the Houſe of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons, and a derogation to them, for the Lords to be Beginners in mov<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:63248:19"/>them to lay any charge upon the People: And that it is the Priviledge of the Houſe of Commons, to have it ariſe from themſelves.</item>
                  <item>2. That it is ſo acknowledged by the King and Lords.</item>
                  <item>3. That upon the Complaint of the Commons, that it is a breach of their Priviledge for the Lords to begin and propound the granting of a Subſidy, and the King and Lords joyning, and ſo declaring it likewiſe, It becomes here a Law, that is, a De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claratory Law of a thing which was before, not a Creating Law of a new thing.</item>
                  <item>4. For it appears to have been a thing formerly ſo ſetled, in regard it is here declared to be the manner and forme accuſtomed, for the Speaker of the Houſe of Commons to be the Perſon from whom the King muſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive the notice of ſuch a Grant, and to be he that muſt preſent it; which ſhews that the Houſe of Commons hath ſomething proper and peculiar unto them in this Grant, ſince it muſt be received from their hand, (for it is their act the preſenting of it, and their Speaker is but the Conduit-pipe to
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:63248:19"/>convey it from them.)</item>
               </list>
And this can only be, that they are to have the beginning of it, to be the firſt Movers and Propoſers of all ſuch Grants: But all things elſe concerning thoſe Grants, as the preparing and modelling and fitting them in all circumſtances, and reducing the ſums to a juſt and due meaſure (if there be cauſe for it) and then the giving them to the King, that is, making a Law whereby they are given to him: and that which was before part of the Eſtate of the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject to be now transferred to the King, and made to be his Right, and his proper goods, and he impowered to levy it; this (wee ſay) to be ſtill the joynt-work of both Houſes, and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qually in the one, as in the other. For in the fifth place it is manifeſt hence likewiſe, that the Lords have their ſhare in the Grant, and that they have power to make ſuch alteration in it, as may fit it for their aſſent; for that Act of Parliament ſaith,
<list>
                  <item>1. That they ſhall debate it, and confer of it among themſelves.</item>
                  <item>2. They may then ſo alter it and frame it, as that they may
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:63248:20"/>aſſent to it; which is the end of their debating it.</item>
                  <item>3. They muſt aſſent to it, before the Speaker of the Houſe of Commons can preſent it.</item>
                  <item>4. The King is to give thanks for it to them, as well as to the Commons: And it cannot be thought that he will thank them for nothing, that is, for a thing in which they have power to do no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing.</item>
                  <item>5. And laſtly, The King by this Act provides for the preſervation of the Priviledge and Liberty of the Houſe of Lords in thoſe Grants unto him, as well as of the Houſe of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons, which had been infringed: And what was this Liberty, but freedom of debate, not to be locked up any more with a previous Vote, as they were then, upon the King's propound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the matter to them, and they coming to a preſent reſolution in the Kings preſence: and accordingly is the Act intituled, <hi>Indemnitee des Seignours et Communes.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>But may it not ſtill be objected, that by what hath been hitherto ſaid, the Lords may adde to, as well as abate and take from the charge? Not at all:
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:63248:20"/>For it hath been ſaid they cannot be the firſt movers and beginners of any charge upon the People; And then they cannot adde any thing: For ſo much as they adde to any Sum pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed by the Commons, they do for ſo much begin a new charge: there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore in all their communings and debatings, the reſult can be only to moderate, and abate the charge, if there be cauſe for it, not to aug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment it.</p>
            <p>As in 4 <hi>R.</hi> 2. n. 11, 12. A great Sum having been demanded by the King, and the great Officers and Councel having delivered in a Schedule con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining divers particular charges, amounting to 150000 <abbr>
                  <hi>l.</hi>
               </abbr> The Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons come before the Lords, and deſire of them a moderation of that Sum, and that it would pleaſe them to conſider how it might be levied; So certainly it was then the opinion of the Houſe of Commons, that the Lords had power to conſider of and leſſen the charge of the People, and to moderate demands; for they de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire them to exerciſe that power:
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:63248:21"/>But it will be ſaid, This was demand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed onely by the King; but the Houſe of Commons had not impoſed that Summe, for then their Lordſhips could not have medled with leſſening it: This doth not at all alter the Caſe, being it was in order to a Bill to be paſſed for laying ſuch a Tax upon the People. But to prove that they have abated of a Summe impoſed by the Houſe of Commons, Wee will goe no further then this very Parliament in the 14th year of the King, in the Bill for enlarging and repairing of common High-wayes, for which pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe the Houſe of Commons had a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greed upon a Rate of 12 <abbr>
                  <hi>d.</hi>
               </abbr> in the Pound, to be levied upon the Inha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitants of Pariſhes contributory to thoſe Repairs, the Lords brought it down to 6 <abbr>
                  <hi>d.</hi>
               </abbr> And the Houſe of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons agreed to it.</p>
            <p>But perhaps they will ſay, That this is not to the purpoſe, for that the Point in controverſie, is not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the Abatement of any charge that ſhould be laid in general upon the Subject; but only for that, which
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:63248:21"/>is impoſed upon Merchandize: As if the one did not neceſſarily follow the other: For if the Lords can abate Taxes at large laid upon the People, with much ſtronger reaſon may they abate an Impoſition upon Merchan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dize exported or Imported; And if they have not power to abate in this which concerns only Merchants, much leſs can it be thought they ſhould doe it in the other, which concerns the whole Kingdome. Which the Houſe of Commons did well foreſee, and therefore it is that they are ſo Poſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive in their Aſſertion, that <hi>It is their fundamental right to impoſe all charge upon Merchandize, for Matter, Mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure and Time, unalterably as to the Lords;</hi> which how they doe make good and maintaine, by their Preſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dents and Arguments, wee will now in few words examine, though by what hath been already ſaid, the contrary ſeems to have been ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciently proved.</p>
            <p>It is true, that at the former Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference the Lords were told, <hi>That the Houſe of Commons had narrowed the
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:63248:22"/>ground, and reduced the Queſtion to this ſingle point of laying rates and impoſitions upon Merehandize only, and not upon the Subject in general.</hi> Wherein the Lords conceive them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves very kindly dealt with, That the Houſe of Commons hath been pleaſed to make choice of that to be diſputed by them, whereto their Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhips have the cleareſt right, to be at leaſt Joynt-tennants with them; and they the leaſt pretenſions to challenge it wholly to themſelves: For in char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging the People, the Houſe of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons will perhaps ſay, they ought to be the ſole Arbiters, in regard they take upon them to be their ſole Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſentatives, and to be Truſtees for them, and truſted by them with all their concerns: (which yet will not be granted, that they repreſent all the People; for how many thouſands are there in every County whom they doe not Repreſent, and who have no voice in their Elections, and ſo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer no truſt upon them?) but they cannot have any the leaſt pretenſions to be ſole in laying burthens upon
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:63248:22"/>Trade, and Rates upon Merchandize, which even for our Home-Commo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dities, and where the naturall borne Subject is concerned, is much de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pending upon, and regulated by Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, and Agreements, and Negotia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions with other Princes and States, over which the Houſe of Commons will not pretend to have any autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, either for governance or inſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, ſo cannot eaſily judge, what is fit or not fit to be impoſed: But then for Merchants Strangers, and their Goods, what colour, what ſhaddow of reaſon, can the Houſe of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons have to pretend any power to lay a charge upon them, and diſpoſe of their Eſtates? The whole Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment indeed hath power over them, as it hath upon whatſoever comes within the Kings Dominions, whether Perſons or Goods, though never ſo forreign: All which (while here) owe a local Subiection to the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and Laws of this Kingdom, but to either Houſe ſingly, none at all; being only ſubject and bound to ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit to what is impoſed upon them by
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:63248:23"/>the whole State making it a Law; but cannot be ſuppoſed to be within the diſpoſition and gift of the Houſe of Commons alone.</p>
            <p>Yet they ſay, <hi>They have been poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed of this power in all Ages, and ſind not one grant of Tunnage and Poundage, that is not barely the gift of the Commons.</hi> And well is it pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved by the Statute of 3 <hi>E.</hi> 1. as hath been ſhewed already, by reading <hi>Communitas conceſſerunt</hi> and leaving out the principal word <hi>Mercatorum,</hi> which ſhews it to have been a Grant of the Merchants, not of the Houſe of Commons, as they would under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand it. And the ſeveral Preſidents cited by the Lords, <hi>When the two Hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes did confer and adviſe together about granting of Aides to the King;</hi> by which the Lords did prove the power exerciſed by their Anceſtors, of delivering their advice and opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions, and giving their Votes in point of Subſidies and Taxes, they would evade by drawing a contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry inference, That is, <hi>All Aydes</hi> (ſaid they) <hi>muſt begin with the Commons,
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:63248:23"/>for elſe the Lords needed not to have conferred, but have ſent down a Bill: So being begun by the Commons, the Lords can neither alter nor diminiſh, elſe why adjuſt matters by private Conference before-hand, if they might have reformed it afterwards?</hi> The firſt part of this is acknowledged, and the ground-work is good, That the Grants muſt begin with the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons, but the ſuperſtructure upon it is very falſe and deceitful: For cleane contrary, It is therefore good to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſt the matter beforehand, and then make but one worke of it, becauſe elſe the Lords, if they be unſatisfied, will alter what the Houſe of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons had taken a great deal of pains to compleat and finiſh, which will be a new buſineſs, take up more time, and cauſe more trouble: Whereas if the Lords had not power to change any thing, it were to no purpoſe to confer and ſatisfie them before-hand, for ſatisfied or not ſatisfied, they could alter nothing, but muſt ſit down and paſs whatever the Houſe of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons had ſent up to them. This was
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:63248:24"/>the true reaſon of thoſe previous Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferences, which ſometimes were pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded by the King, ſometimes de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired by the Commons, but ſtill to expedite, and facilitate the buſineſs, and only for that end. Which makes good all thoſe Preſidents, <hi>viz.</hi> 14th. 22th. 29th. 47th. and 51th. <hi>E.</hi> 3. the 4th. and 6th. <hi>R.</hi> 2. and the 7th. of King <hi>James,</hi> which were cited by the Lords concerning thoſe Conferences between the two Houſes about mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of Money, whether for raiſing or for diſpoſing of them: and leaves them ſtrong evidences and unſhaken proofs of that Right, and Power, and Intereſt, which the Houſe of Lords hath in all ſuch matters, whether of Aides given to the King, or Moneys raiſed upon the People for the preſent defenſe of the Kingdom, and imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately ordered to be applyed to that purpoſe: And this acknowledged even by the Houſe of Commons themſelves, as appears by their often Addreſſes to the Lords deſiring their help and aſſiſtance in it.</p>
            <p>As for the Caſe of 14 <hi>E.</hi> 3. it was
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:63248:24"/>made uſe of by the Lords only to prove, that there had been <hi>Grand trete et parlance entre les Grantz et les Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>es,</hi> great treating and conferring between them. As for what was ſaid after of the Nones being then granted, or having been granted be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore to be then appointed to be ſold for the preſent raiſing of Money, which was mentioned at the Confe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence, as if the Lords had committed ſome miſtake in their citing of this Preſident, alters not the Caſe. The Conference about the preſent raiſing of Money in that way, and the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons of themſelves not able to doe it without the Conjunction of the Lords, is a Preſident undeniable of the Lords Power and Intereſt in mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of that nature: Yet who reads the Record thorough will find, that there was 40 <abbr>
                  <hi>s.</hi>
               </abbr> upon the Sack of Wool granted for Cuſtome, and 20000 Sacks of Wool to be taken up for the King, in whoſe hands ſoever found, and the price ſet, one mark upon a Sack leſs than was agreed at <hi>Nottingham,</hi> the Owners to be reim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burſed
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:63248:25"/>out of the Nones of the ſecond year. And this was a propoſition made by the Lords, and aſſented to by the Commons.</p>
            <p>Then their obſervation upon the 22 <hi>E.</hi> 3. n. 3. muſt not be paſſed by: They will have it to prove expreſly that the Commons granted 3 Fifteens, as if they had done it alone without the Lords; (which how impoſſible it is, need not be ſaid, it ſpeaks it ſelf; for it cannot be imagined that one Houſe alone could make an Act of Parliament). But this was meer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly a propoſition of the Houſe of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons, in Anſwer to what they had received in command from the King, as appears by the Record it ſelf. The words are, <hi>Sur ce fut commande as Chinalers des Contees et autres des Communes qils ſe deueroient treter enſemble, et prendre bon anys, &amp;c. Et de ſe qils ent ſentirent le deveroient monſtrer a noſtre Seigneur le Roy et a les Grants, &amp;c.</hi> Then after ſome dayes debating it among themſelves, they came up to the Houſe of Lords, and ſirſt make great complaints of
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:63248:25"/>their many preſſures, then make ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral requeſts, and declare certain con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions, which conditions obſerved, &amp; their requeſts granted, they then ſay, they give three fifteens. Let any man now judge, if this was any more than a bare propoſition of the Houſe of Commons, which they made to the King and the Houſe of Lords; And if this could be the Granting of a Subſidy: But indeed the King and Lords conſenting and joyning in it; It was then a perfect grant, ſetled by a Law. To ſay the truth of this Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, no great formality was ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved in it; It was very ſhort by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of the Plague, as was declared at the opening of the next Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, which was 25. n. 5. in theſe words, <hi>Ceſt aſſaver l'an de ſon Regne vintiſme ſecond il ſiſt ſommondre ſon Parlement a Weſtminſter, lequel ſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bla puis a luy et a ſon Conſeil, que ne ſe poeit bonement tenir adonques, pur cauſe de la peſtilence q'eſtoit bien aſpre a meſme temps, et par tant il ſiſt releſſer le dit ſommons adonques, &amp;c.</hi> So as no good meaſure can well
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:63248:26"/>be taken from any thing done this Parliament.</p>
            <p>Much need not be ſaid neither to their endeavour of proving the <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munitas</hi> 3. <hi>E.</hi> 1. to be underſtood to be the Communalty of <hi>England</hi> by the recital of that Statute, in a Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute made after in 25 <hi>E.</hi> 1. c. 7. called <hi>Conſirmationes Chartarum,</hi> ſince it hath already been made out by the Record, That that Grant in 3 <hi>tio.</hi> was by the <hi>Communitas Mercatorum.</hi> But how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever, a ſhort mention made in a Recital, can be no Reſtrictive proof; that is to ſay, not a proof to limit and reſtrain the ſenſe, when more is expreſſed, or may be underſtood in the Act it ſelf at large.</p>
            <p>And therefore their argumentation concerning thoſe Statutes of <hi>E.</hi> 6. can no ways be allowed. In the 2 &amp; 3 <hi>E.</hi> 6. c. 36. A Subſidy is given, and the ſtile is, <hi>Wee the Kings Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſties faithful, loving and obedient Subjects the Lords and Commons doe grant, &amp;c.</hi> This Statute (he ſaith) is recited in 3 &amp; 4 <hi>E.</hi> 6. c. 23. And there it is acknowledged to be only a
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:63248:26"/>Grant of the Commons: The words are theſe, <hi>That where in the laſt Seſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of this preſent Parliament, your humble and faithful Subjects the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons in the ſaid Parliament aſſembled with the aſſent of the Lords Spiritual and Temporal Granted, &amp;c.</hi> Now firſt, This is not ſaid to be onely the Grant of the Commons, for the Lords joyne and give their aſſent to it. Secondly, If the Commons only had been mentioned reſtrictively in this Recital, the Act it ſelf ſaying ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſly, <hi>That the Lords and Commons Granted,</hi> ſhould the Recital be of more validity to declare what was enacted, than the Act it ſelf? In the third place it may be obſerved, That the Act ſaying, <hi>The Lords and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons doe Grant,</hi> And the Recital of that Act ſaying, <hi>It was the Commons with the aſſent of the Lords,</hi> It muſt follow that in the Judgement of the Parliament then, theſe two forms of expreſſing the Grant of a Subſidy did ſignifie one and the ſame thing, and they may be promiſcuouſly uſed without any variation of the ſenſe;
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:63248:27"/>ſo that in all Acts of Subſidies where wee find it ſaid, <hi>Wee the Commons doe with the aſſent of the Lords grant ſo and ſo,</hi> it is as much as if it had been ſaid, <hi>Wee the Lords and Commons doe grant, &amp;c.</hi> which overthrows all that the Houſe of Commons hath al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged or can alledge to make it to be <hi>their gift alone, and the Lords to have no part in it; And to prove it</hi> (ſay they) <hi>the ſtile hath been altered, and the Acts doe now run for the moſt part, Wee the Commons with the aſſent of the Lords, &amp;c.</hi> But it is anſwered, though the ſtile be changed, the ſenſe continues the ſame.</p>
            <p>And 2 <hi>R.</hi> 2. n. 37. The Houſe of Commons themſelves are ſaid but to <hi>Give their aſſent</hi> to an Impoſition, which had his riſe in the Houſe of Lords. The Caſe was thus, Upon a Reference from the Houſe of Lords to the Earl of <hi>Northumberland,</hi> and the Maior of <hi>London,</hi> with ſome Merchants joyned to them, ſix Veſſels were ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed for the guarding of the Nor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thern Seas infeſted by Pirates, who had landed and plundered the Town
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:63248:27"/>of <hi>Scarborough:</hi> and for defraying the charge of thoſe Veſſels, an Impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition was laid upon Ships that paſſed through thoſe Seas of 6 <abbr>
                  <hi>d.</hi>
               </abbr>
               <hi>per</hi> Tun, excepting <hi>Flemiſh</hi> Ships bound for <hi>London,</hi> and ſuch as carried Wools and Woolfells to <hi>Calais,</hi> and 6 <abbr>
                  <hi>d.</hi>
               </abbr> 
               <hi>per</hi> Tun a week upon Ships that fiſhed for Herring; and upon all other Fiſher-boats 6 <abbr>
                  <hi>d.</hi>
               </abbr> 
               <hi>per</hi> Tun every three weeks. This had paſſed in the Houſe of Lords, unknown (it ſeems) to the Houſe of Commons: for the Record ſaith, they petitioned the King, that care might be had of thoſe Seas, and of the Town of <hi>Scarborough.</hi> The Anſwer is, <hi>Remede ent eſt ordeinez, per maniere comme le Conte de Nor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thumberland et le Mair de Londres qi furent aſſignez en Parlement de treter ſur cette biſoigne le ſachent plus au plein declarer,</hi> That already there is a remedy ordeined in it, as the Earl of <hi>Northumberland</hi> and Maior of <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don,</hi> who were appointed by the Parliament to treat, of that buſineſs, could more fully informe them; which they did, and the Commons gave
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:63248:28"/>their Aſſent to it, as is expreſſed in a Schedule annexed, which contains the particulars of that tranſaction. So then the ſtile of <hi>Giving an Aſſent</hi> can not be ſaid to be wholly and ſolely appropriated to the Houſe of Lords, and made a mark of their having no part nor portion in the giving of thoſe Subſidies, ſince the ſame is likewiſe ſaid of the Houſe of Commons.</p>
            <p>As for the <hi>Indemnity of the Lords and Commons</hi> 9 H. 4. It hath been already ſpoken to, and clearly prov<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed out of it, that the Lords are very far from being by it ſecluded to be noe parties to the Grant, but that they ſhould not be the Beginners of it, is confeſſed: And that was it, which was then the Grievance to the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons, that the Lords had already concluded the Aide to the King, and declared it ſo to the Commons, not for demanding a Committee to confer with about it, as was alledged at the Conference.</p>
            <p>As for the Book-Caſe of 33 <hi>H.</hi> 6. which they ſay is the weakeſt of all,
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:63248:28"/>is a thing eaſily ſaid, but not ſo eaſily made good; for others conceive it a very ſtrong proof of the Lords aſſertion of their Intereſt in granting of Subſidies: it is brought there as an inſtance of the Proceedings of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, of which the Judges deſired to be informed, upon occaſion of a buſineſs depending before them, in which there had paſſed an Act of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, and therefore they ſent for <hi>Kirkeby</hi> of the Rolls (as the Book ſtiles him) and for <hi>Faux</hi> the Clerk of the Parliament, to receive informa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion from them: They come, and <hi>Kirkeby</hi> ſpeaks and lays down this for a Rule, <hi>That if the Lords make an al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teration to a Bill, which may well ſtand with that which the Commons have done, they need not ſend this Bill back to the Houſe of Commons.</hi> And of this they give an inſtance, which is this, <hi>If</hi> (ſay they) <hi>the Commons have ſent up a Bill of Tunnage and Poundage to continue for four years, and the Lords they alter it to two years, it need not be ſent down againe to the Houſe of Commons:</hi> And the
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:63248:29"/>reaſon is, becauſe it may ſtand with the grant of the Commons, for both Lords and Commons have granted it for two years. This was the Caſe to which were taken ſeveral excep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, 1. <hi>That it was onely the opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion of the Clerk of the Parliament, not of the Judges;</hi> To which is an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered, That if it was ſo, none could better know the courſe of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, than the Clerk of the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, who was therefore ſent for by the Judges to informe them; nor durſt he have delivered that in Court for an inſtance, of the courſe and uſage of Parliament, if it had been a thing not practiſed in Parliament. Nor is it to be believed, that thoſe Judges could be ſo ignorant of the proceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings of Parliament, particularly of the manner of granting Subſidies, in which every man is concerned, as not they to have known, if or no the Clerk did give a true inſtance of a matter in fact: And their allowing of it, was a kind of declaring their opinions in the Caſe. But it was not the Clerk of the Parliament, that
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:63248:29"/>gave that account to the Judges, though it be true that <hi>Faux</hi> the Clerk of the Parliament agreed to it, but <hi>Kirkeby</hi> (who was in truth Maſter of the Rolls) ſaid it in the name of both: whoſe authority ſhould be of weight, being one in that great place, which is ranked in the Statute 12 <hi>R.</hi> 2. c. 2. before the two Chief Juſtices, by the name of Clerk of the Rolls, by which name that Officer was anciently cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, and was firſt in any Statute ſtiled Maſter of the Rolls, 11 <hi>H.</hi> 7. c. 18. <hi>Kirkeby</hi> held this Office, which was granted to him in reverſion after <hi>John Stopindon,</hi> by a Patent confirmed by Parliament, bearing date 20 <hi>Martii</hi> 25 <hi>H.</hi> 6. p. 1. m. 7. And ſo <hi>Brooke</hi> ſtiles him, Clerk of the Rolls of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, not Clerk of the Parliament (as he was termed at the Conference ſlightly enough) which title <hi>Brooke</hi> gives to <hi>Faux,</hi> as the Year-booke doth. Nor is the authority of the Year-booke it ſelf to be ſet ſo light by, having been compiled by the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleſt Students at Law appointed for that worke, allowed and approved
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:63248:30"/>by the Judges then, and by all the Judges and Lawyers ever ſince. Their ſecond exception is, <hi>That it was a Caſe put by the By, and not pertinent to the matter there in hand:</hi> Which may be urged rather an Argument for it than againſt it, there being the leſs reaſon to apprehend, that there was any byaſs of affection or prejudice to lead them to ſuch a declaration, as too often there is, when men come to ſpeak their opinions concerning things in conteſt between party and party. Thirdly, <hi>That it is againſt the conſtant uſage of Parliament, for that then the Lords may chuſe whether they will ſend downe the Bill, after they have made an Abatement.</hi> It is acknowledged, that the Lords doe now uſe to ſend back a Bill, if any the leaſt alteration be made in it; but why formerly it might not have been ſometimes otherwiſe practiſed, no convincing reaſon can be given: Wee know many things have been chang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in Parliaments, and every where elſe: Some things have been uſed heretofore, which are not now; and
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:63248:30"/>ſome things are now, which may not be hereafter. One that ſhould move now in Parliament, to have a Bill read again, which hath already been read three times, would not ſpeed with his motion, but be laughed at for his labour: Yet heretofore Bills, eſpecially Bills of Subſidy were com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly read four times, and ſometimes oftener. So Conferences between the Houſes were commonly demanded to be by a certain number, which is now never done; nay, would it not be thought a breach of Priviledge, and an impoſing upon the other Houſe, if it ſhould be demanded? Heretofore the Houſe of Commons could not pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh any of their own Members, nor any body elſe, that had broken their Priviledges; but they made their complaints to the Houſe of Lords, and they did them juſtice; but they will tell you, it is not ſo uſed now: and yet becauſe it is not ſo now, they will not make it an Argument that it was not ſo then, nor deny the truth of an inſtance brought of what was done then: No more can they with reaſon
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:63248:31"/>ſay, the Clerk of the Parliament, or the Maſter of the Rolls, who by that Book Caſe appears to have declared ſuch a thing to have been in thoſe times the uſage of Parliament, ſaid falſe, becauſe it is not ſo in theſe times. The fourth objection is, that the Clerk ſaith, <hi>The Lords may increaſe Impoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions alſo, which part of the Caſe</hi> (they ſaid) <hi>their Lordſhips thought not fit to cite.</hi> It is true they did not cite it, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe that part of the Book-Caſe was out of the preſent Caſe, the Lords not pretending to a power of increa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing Impoſitions. Nor is it ſtrange, if it was not then ſo clear, but that the Lords might adde, when once the Commons had begun a Tax, though not begin one themſelves, which now is out of queſtion upon better conſideration by a neceſſary infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence, that as much as the Lords doe adde to any Impoſition, they doe for ſo much begin an Impoſition, though the Bill which charges the Subject, begin not in their Houſe.</p>
            <p>And certainly they miſplace the Querie in <hi>Brooke,</hi> if they apply it to
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:63248:31"/>that part of this Caſe, which concerns the Lords abating two years, when the Commons had given four, as any body may ſee, that will peruſe the paſſage. It is <hi>Part</hi> 2. <hi>fol.</hi> 116. <hi>Tit.</hi> Parliament and Statutes, 4. The Quae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie there is put onely to what is ſaid of ſending the Bill back againe to the Commons, the words are, <hi>Comme ſi les Commons graunte poundage pur quatuor ans, et les Seigneurs graunt niſi pur deuxans, ceo ne ſera rebaile as Commons (Quaere inde)</hi> It appears what it is that he makes his <hi>Quaere</hi> by that which follows, where he delivers his opinion of the forme uſed in the tranſmitting Bills from one Houſe to an other. He ſaith, <hi>That if a Bill begin in the Houſe of Lords, and there paſs, they doe not uſe to indorſe it, but ſend it downe to the Commons, and if thyy paſs it, it is then indorſed</hi> Les Commons ſont aſſentans; <hi>and this ſhews it had already paſſed the Lords, and their aſſent is to what the Lords had paſſed;</hi> upon which he infers, <hi>Et ideo ceſt acte ſupra neſt bon pur ceoque il ne fuit rebaile as Commons.</hi> There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:63248:32"/>the Act above-mentioned is not good, becauſe it was not ſent back to the Commons: And this he makes to be his reaſon, why it was not good, becauſe it was not ſent back. But he makes not any ſcruple at all of the Lords cutting off the two years. This ſeems very plaine to have been his meaning: Yet a <hi>Quaere</hi> may be put upon what <hi>Brooke</hi> himſelf ſaith, that the Lords doe not uſe to endorſe it, if it begins with them, for they doe write upon it now, and certainly did then, <hi>Soit baille aux Communs.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Then for <hi>Dyer Mic.</hi> 30 <hi>H.</hi> 8. 22. It is true the words are as they were quoted at the Conference, and no body can deny what they import, That the Commons doe grant; but <hi>Dyer</hi> ſaith not, that they doe it ſingly and alone without the Lords. To give a true judgement of his meaning, one muſt conſider his end and ſcope in ſaying this, it was to ſhew the diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence betwixt the old Cuſtomes, and a Subſidy of Tunnage and Poundage; The Cuſtomes he ſaith are the Kings inheritance, and due to him by the
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:63248:32"/>Common Law, and therefore the firſt Statute that mentions Cuſtomes, 14 <hi>E.</hi> 3. he ſaith, doth not grant any thing, but abridges the Kings power, that he ſhall not take more than half a mark for a Sack of Wooll, and half a mark for a laſt of Leather: But the Subſidy is a Tax aſſeſſed by Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and Granted to the King by the Commons for his life onely, for de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence of the Seas; The one is Inheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, the other is a Grant; but to define and deſcribe what kinde of Grant, and in what manner granted, whether by one or both Houſes, with all the circumſtances of it, was certainly not at all in that Reverend Judges thought. This then is no ſuch Judicial determination of the Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion, as they would make it.</p>
            <p>From thence they come to the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſoes in the Bill of 1 <hi>H.</hi> 8. in which, as in the Bill it ſelf, and their conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion upon it, <hi>viz. That they are of no force, unleſs it be againſt the Lords,</hi> there is certainly a great miſtake; They ſay, that by the Lords Journal the Caſe is this, <hi>That the Bill did not paſs
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:63248:33"/>till the</hi> 3 <hi>of</hi> H. 8. <hi>That the Lords aſſented to it the</hi> 43d <hi>day of the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, That the</hi> 45th <hi>day two pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſoes came in; one touching the Merchants of the Hans Towns, the other touching the Merchants of the Staple at</hi> Calais, <hi>both ſigned by the King; And that the Chancellor and Biſhop of</hi> Winton <hi>did declare that the ſigning of thoſe Proviſoes by the Kings own hand, was enough with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the conſent of either Houſe:</hi> Then they give reaſons why they prove no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing.
<list>
                  <item>1. <hi>For that they were ſigned by the King.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>2. <hi>For that they were brought in againſt all courſe of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liaments, after the Bill paſſed.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>3. <hi>That the Proviſoes were nothing but a ſav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of former rights.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>4. <hi>That the Journal declares, that the King with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out thoſe Proviſoes might have done the ſame thing by his Prerogative.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
This is the Narrative which they gave us.</p>
            <p>The truth is this, In the firſt place, the Lords did not cite, nor inſiſt upon two Proviſoes, but onely upon one, that which concerned the Merchants
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:63248:33"/>of the Staple, which Proviſo was ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded then by the Houſe of Lords, who meddled not with that which con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned the Hans Towns, which was a Proviſo ſent up with the Bill from the Houſe of Commons. The progreſs of this Bill was thus, all of it in the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament of 1 <hi>H.</hi> 8. for that which was ſaid at the Conference, that the Bill it ſelf paſſed not till the 3 <hi>H.</hi> 8. is a groſs miſtake: That was another Bill of Subſidy, which was given that Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament 3 <hi>H.</hi> 8. and it is true; wee find in the Journal that the 45th day of that Parliament of 3<hi>tio.</hi> the Chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellor and Biſhop of <hi>Wincheſter</hi> did declare ſuch a thing concerning the Merchants of the Hans Towns, in theſe words, <hi>Et dictum &amp; decretum eſt per Dominum Cancellarium &amp; Epiſcopum Winton. quoad Proviſ. pro Mercatoribus de Hanſa quod Proviſ. pro ipſis per ipſum Regem ſignatum ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciet eis abſ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> aſſenſu Dominorum &amp; Domus Communis;</hi> Theſe were ſtran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers with whom the Parliament had nothing to doe, ſo ſuch a Declaration might be concerning them: But the
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:63248:34"/>Proviſoe inſiſted upon by the Lords was concerning the Merchants of the Staple natural borne Subjects: And be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides, that which the Houſe of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons went upon at the Conference, was clean another thing, a Proviſoe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lating to an other Bill, and paſſed in an other Parliament: For 1 <hi>H.</hi> 8. 23d day of the Parliament, and 16th of <hi>Febr.</hi> upon a <hi>Saturday</hi> this Bill which is now in queſtion came up to the Lords from the Houſe of Commons, <hi>cum Proviſo pro Mercatoribus de la Hanſa Theuto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicorum;</hi> at the head of this Proviſo, are theſe words, <hi>Soit baille aux Seig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neurs,</hi> and at the foot, theſe, <hi>Les Seig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neurs ont aſſentus.</hi> Then the 27th day of the Parliament, which was <hi>Thurſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day</hi> the 21 of <hi>Febr.</hi> the Lords paſſed the Proviſoe for the Merchants of the Staple which had begun in their Houſe, the words are, <hi>Item Proviſo pro Mercatoribus Stapule de Calais, lecta eſt ſecundo &amp; tertio, &amp; miſſa in Domum inferiorem per Clericum Coro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nae,</hi> and theſe words at the top of it; <hi>Soit baille aux Communs,</hi> and at the foot theſe, <hi>A Cette proviſion les Côes
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:63248:34"/>ſont aſſentus.</hi> Then the 29th day, which was the laſt day of the Parliament, the Bill with the two Proviſoes an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nexed were delivered to Sir <hi>Thomas Lovel</hi> at the Bar, <hi>Actus Subſidii cum duabus Proviſ annex. liberati Thomae Lovel militi cum Sociis ad Barram,</hi> ſaith the Journal.</p>
            <p>This bare relation juſtifies enough the Lords citing of that Proviſo, by which the Merchants of <hi>Calais</hi> are excepted from their being lyable to any of the payments impoſed by that Bill of Subſidy of 1<hi rend="sup">mo</hi>. <hi>H</hi> 8. To ſay it was but a Saving of former rights ſignifies nothing: for no queſtion, the Lords would not have done it without good cauſe for it, (nor will they at any time make any abatement, but for good cauſe:) but ſtill they ſaved to the Merchants of <hi>England,</hi> their right, which the Commons had taken away. And then here was no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing againſt the courſe of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, the Proviſo regularly added by the Lords, and ſent down to the Houſe of Commons in due manner, and afterwards paſſed by the King with the Bill.</p>
            <pb n="66" facs="tcp:63248:35"/>
            <p>Then for the Kings ſigning it, which the Manager of the Conference made to be ſo great a matter: if he would have peruſed the Records of <hi>H.</hi> 8. he would have ſeen, that in thoſe times the King ſtill ſigned all the Bills he paſſed, and all the Proviſoes annexed he ſigned likewiſe with his own hand, only Bills of Subſidy he ſigned not: But the Proviſoes an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nexed to Bills of Subſidy, which were to eaſe and diſcharge any perſons, thoſe he alſo ſigned; and therefore the other Proviſoe concerning the <hi>Hans-Towns,</hi> which was annexed to the Bill, when it came up from the Houſe of Commons, was likewiſe ſign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by the King. So as the Kings ſigning this Proviſoe concerning the Merchants of <hi>Calais,</hi> cited by the Lords alters not the Caſe, and makes nothing againſt its proving an inhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent Power and Authority to be in the Houſe of Peers of adding ſuch Proviſoes, or making abatements in Bills of Subſidy, whenſoever they ſee cauſe for it. As they did 1 <hi>Eliz.</hi> when they gave reſpite to the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:63248:35"/>of <hi>Wales,</hi> and the County Pala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tine of <hi>Cheſter,</hi> for paying the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidy (given that Parliament) a year after all the reſt of the Kingdom, which was an eaſing of them for that time.</p>
            <p>And for what is ſaid of the Grant 1 <hi>H.</hi> 8. that it was of the Commons alone, it was, as many other Grants then were, <hi>The Commons by the aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent of the Lords, &amp;c.</hi> which expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion is ſometimes uſed, as ſignifying the ſame thing with the other, <hi>We the Lords and Commons do grant, &amp;c.</hi> as 37 <hi>H.</hi> 8. the only printed Act of Subſidy in all his reign, which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gins thus, <hi>We the Kings Majeſties moſt humble, faithful, and obedient Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects, the Lords Spiritual and Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poral, and the Commons in this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Parliament aſſembled,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>have conſulted together, and determined to beſeech His Majeſty moſt humbly to accept, and graciouſly to receive, at our hands the ſimple token or gift which we do herewith preſent to His Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty, freely with one conſent grant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the ſame; moſt humbly beſeech<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:63248:36"/>His Majeſty to accept the ſame, as it pleaſed the great King</hi> Alexan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der <hi>to receive thankfully a Cup of wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of a poor man by the high-way<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide, &amp;c.</hi> And a little after they ſay, <hi>Wherefore we the ſaid Lords and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons do by our mutual Aſſents and Agreements with one whole voice and hearty good will, by the authority of this preſent Parliament give and grant to the Kings Highneſs, &amp;c.</hi> Here then is but one conſent, one whole voice, one hearty good-will to give and grant, and one Act of giving and granting of the Lords and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons, and yet the Lords muſt have no hand in this giving, as was told them at this Conference. And they are told further, <hi>That the thanks was given to the Commons alone,</hi> and that is true; it was it ſeems the Kings pleaſure ſo to do: But this courſe was not always obſerved, ſometimes both were thanked, and the Law is they ſhould be ſo in the Indemnity of Lords and Commons, 9 <hi>H.</hi> 4. Nor can the Act of a King, uſing his plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, ſometimes to vary from the exact<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:63248:36"/>of a Law, make an alteration in the nature and force of that Law, but that ſtill it remains the ſame, to ſhew what then ſhould have been done, however the King was pleaſed to do otherwiſe, and what will be done, or at leaſt ought to be done at an other time.</p>
            <p>And now we will go with them to <hi>Walſingham,</hi> and ſee if Hiſtory makes more for them than Records; though neither is Hiſtory a ſufficient proof for things of this nature, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther is <hi>Walſinghams,</hi> or any of thoſe <hi>Moncks</hi> Writings, the moſt authen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tick Hiſtory in the world: But let us ſee what <hi>Walſingham</hi> ſaith, <hi>p.</hi> 475. he ſaith, <hi>His diebus Clerus &amp; popu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lus primo quintam decimam, &amp; poſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modum triceſimam bonorum ſuorum Regi Angliae in Subſidium conceſſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>runt.</hi> And <hi>p.</hi> 488. he ſaith, <hi>Pro con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmatione harum rerum omnium de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit Populus Anglicanus Regi denari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um nonum bonorum ſuorum, &amp; Cle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rus Cantuarienſis decimum, &amp; Clerus Eboracenſis quintum, quia proprior damno fuit.</hi> What doth this ſignifie?
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:63248:37"/>but that the Laity gave ſo much, and the Clergy ſo much; and certainly the Lords will be acknowledged to be part of the Laity, therefore the Laity giving they are comprehend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. An other quotation was urged from <hi>p.</hi> 566. The words are, <hi>Eo tempore incohatum eſt Parliamentum, quod protelabatur inutiliter fere per an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num, quia poſtquam Parliamentales mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lites diſtuliſſent diu concedere Regi Subſidium, in fine tamen fracti con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſere taxam petitam grandi Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitatis damno.</hi> But how they will prove hence, that the Commons gave this Subſidy alone is difficult to tell. All that can be gathered from it, ſeems to be but this, the Knights in Parliament (which may be taken for the whole Houſe of Commons) held off a long time, but at laſt yielded, and gave the Tax demanded to the great prejudice of the Commonalty? doth it follow therefore, that when the Houſe of Commons had paſſed it at laſt, the Lords did not aſſent and joine in the Grant? Certainly no man will ſay it. And for their laſt
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:63248:37"/>quotation, out of <hi>p.</hi> 564, in <hi>H.</hi> 4<hi rend="sup">ths</hi> time, that <hi>Subſidium denegatum fuit Proceribus renitentibus,</hi> the words are theſe, <hi>In quadrageſima ſequente Rex convenire fecit apud Sanctum Alba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num Clerum Regni<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> Barones, ſed pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceribus renitentibus nil actum fuit:</hi> And no wonder that the Lords diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenting nothing was done; yet whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther this was a Parliament, or only a Great Council <hi>non conſtat,</hi> more like to have been only a Great Council, and that the King had propounded matter of money to them, as he did afterward in the Parliament of the 9th of his Reigne to the Houſe of Lords, and as this very Writer ſaith, that he had done a little before to theſe ſame Barons at <hi>London,</hi> viz. <hi>Poſt Feſtum Purificationis Rex accerſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitis Londiniis regni Baronibus, tract a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bat cum eiſdem de Regni regimine, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que pecuniali ſubventione ſibi feren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>da, ſed proceres Regiis votis tum mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nimè paruere.</hi> All this was but a great Council, and no Parliament, if ſo be <hi>Walſingham</hi> gave a true account of what paſſed; for he doth not men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:63248:38"/>the Commons to have been ſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moned at all, or that they were there: However, were they, or were they not there, it makes nothing for the Managers purpoſe, to prove the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons ſole givers: And then for what he obſerves, that the Lords not A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greeing an Act doth not paſs, is what no man yet did ever doubt of.</p>
            <p>The Statute of 1 <hi>E.</hi> 3. <hi>c.</hi> 6. where the Commons complain, that when they have granted an Aid, and the Taxers had taxed them, and they had paid the money, there was Inquiſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions afterwards, and the Taxers put to fine and ranſome, ſignifies nothing to prove they were the ſole Granters of that Aid.</p>
            <p>And the 18th of <hi>E.</hi> 3. <hi>n.</hi> 14. It was by Agreement, that the Lords ſhould accompany the King, and paſs the Seas with him; And the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons they grant for the Commonalty at large, in the Counties two Fif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teens, and for the Cities and Bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roughs two Tenths; the Record ſaith, <hi>Et pur ceſte cauſe les ditz Grants gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terent de paſſer &amp; lour auenturer oveſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:63248:38"/>lui, &amp; la dite Commune luy gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tà pur meiſme la cauſe ſur certeine fourme deux Quinziſmes de la Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munaltee, &amp; deux Diſmes des Citees &amp; Eurghs,</hi> &amp;c. This was ſometimes pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſed, as hath been already ſhewed both in this Kings time, and in <hi>E.</hi> 4ths and once in Queen <hi>Eliz.</hi> that the two Houſes did agree to act ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verally, as here the Lords to ſerve in perſon, when the Commons gave money: So ſome times the Lords would charge themſelves and their Tenants apart (which in thoſe times was a great part of the Kingdom, and taking in the Clergy, that is, Biſhops, and Abbots, and Priors, who held <hi>per Baroniam,</hi> more than half the Kingdom) and the Commons did charge themſelves a-part, this in an extraordinary way, which altered not the Caſe of their joint Gift, when they would grant Aides in the ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary Parliamentary manner.</p>
            <p>As for what is ſaid of the 36 <hi>E.</hi> 3. <hi>c.</hi> 11. was but taken out of <hi>Poultons</hi> Collection of Statutes in Print; there indeed it is ſaid, <hi>That the three years
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:63248:39"/>Subſidy granted by the Commons to the King ſhall be no example for the time to come.</hi> But if the Record it ſelf had been conſulted with, it would have ſhewed that the Lords and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons granted this Subſidy, it is <hi>n.</hi> 35. where is ſaid, <hi>Les dits Grants et Communes granterent d'un aſſent a noſtre dit Seignieur le Roy un Subſide de Leines Cuirs &amp; Pealx lanutz,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>pur terme de trois ans pleinement ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compliz.</hi> It is true, that in the end of the Record it is ſaid, <hi>Purquelegrant noſtre Seigneur le Roy a la requeſte de ſa Commune lour ad fait Pardon de pluſour Articles d' Eyre.</hi> For which Grant the King at the prayer of the Commons, remits unto them many things for which they were or might be queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned in his Courts. And ſo among the Petitions of the Commons in that Parliament, <hi>n.</hi> 26. they pray, That after the three years expired onely the old Cuſtome may be levied; And they pray, <hi>Que nul Subſide n'autre charge ſoit mis, ne grante ſur les Leines par les Marchaunts ne par nul autre de ſorenaunt ſins aſſent du Parlement,</hi>
               <pb n="75" facs="tcp:63248:39"/>That no Subſidy nor other Charge be laid, neither by the Merchants, nor any body elſe granted upon Wools henceforward without conſent of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament. And the anſwer is, <hi>Il pleſt au Roy;</hi> the King approves it. Is there one word in this Record which makes for the Managers pretenſes? Doth it not expreſly ſay, That this Subſidy was granted by the Lords and Commons? What the Commons make to be their deſire afterwards upon it, is nothing to the Grant. But this appears by it, that the Merchants ſometimes granted ſuch things with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the Parliament, as hath been ſaid before; for the Commons complain of it, and petition againſt it here.</p>
            <p>So the Subſidy granted 21 <hi>R.</hi> 2. <hi>n.</hi> 15. was not by the Commons a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone, for it was by the aſſent of the Biſhops and Lords granted to the King during life; thoſe are the words of the Record, and they ſignifie the ſame thing, as if it had been ſaid, That the Lords and Commons had granted it. This hath been already made out to the full, and thoſe Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutes
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:63248:40"/>of <hi>E.</hi> 6. formerly cited by the Manager himſelf are a proof of it ir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>refragable. For that of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> and 3 <hi>E.</hi> 6. ſays, <hi>The Lords and Commons grant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed a Subſidy;</hi> and the Statute of 3 and 4 <hi>E.</hi> 6. reciting that ſaith, <hi>The Commons granted it with the aſſent of the Lords.</hi> Which ſhews the meaning of the Parliament in thoſe two differing expreſſions to be one and the ſame: But the Manager tells us not what followed upon the grant of this Subſidy, which was that the King gave a general Pardon, and withall the Record ſaith, <hi>Fiſt overt Decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration per ſon bouche de meſme, que ſiles Seigneurs ou Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>es du Roialme qui viendront as Parlments en temps advenir mettent ou facent impedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment ou diſtourbance a contraire del Grante du dite ſubſide des Leins Quirs &amp; Peaux lanutz enſi grauntez a luy a terme de ſa vie, que adonques la dite Grace &amp; Pardon ſoit tout voide, &amp; tout outrement adnulle;</hi> Declared with his own mouth, that if either the Lords or Commons ſhould afterwards in any Parliament give impediment
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:63248:40"/>or diſturbance to this Subſidy of Wool, Leather, and Woollfells ſo granted to him for his life, that then the ſaid Free Grace and Pardon ſhould be wholly void and totally annulled. So it ſeems the King thought that the Lords might make ſome al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teration in the Subſidy, as well as the Commons and feared it: And the Commons themſelves did not gain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſay it, which they would certainly have done, if it had then been a ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral received Poſition, that which hath now been ſo confidently aſſert<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, nay, if it had then been but a queſtion, that the Lords might not meddle in any of theſe Subſidies, nor hinder nor alter any thing, which the Commons would do concerning them. This was not for his turn, and therefore he would take no notice of it. But in truth the very Grant it ſelf ſhews it to be the joint act of both Houſes, and that the Lords had an intereſt in it, as well as the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons: For whoever muſt aſſent to a thing, and that it cannot be diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed of without his aſſent, muſt
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:63248:41"/>queſtionleſs have an intereſt in it.</p>
            <p>The ſame is to be ſaid of 2 <hi>H.</hi> 6. <hi>n.</hi> 14. 31 <hi>H.</hi> 6. <hi>n.</hi> 7, 8, 9, 10. and 8 <hi>E.</hi> 4. <hi>n.</hi> 30. all run, The Commons by aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent of the Lords. In the two firſt of <hi>H.</hi> 6. The Manager hath it ſeems been miſled by the Exact Abridgement, and not conſulting the Rolls; But that of 8 <hi>E.</hi> 4. is ſo <hi>in terminis</hi> in the Abridgement it ſelf, therefore it is ſome wonder how he came to miſtake this, and ranck it amongſt thoſe, which he makes to run in the ſtile of being Granted by the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons alone without any mention of the Lords.</p>
            <p>As he doth alſo miſtake that of the 3 <hi>E.</hi> 4. relying meerly upon the Print of 12 <hi>E.</hi> 4. <hi>c.</hi> 3. where it is indeed re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cited to be by the Commons alone: But if he had reſorted to the Record (which only is an Authentick Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſident) he had ſeen, that there it is in the ſame ſtile as all the reſt. It is <hi>n.</hi> 24. both in the <hi>Memorandum</hi> which is in <hi>Latin</hi> in theſe words, <hi>Communes in praeſenti Parlamento,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>de aſſenſu Dominorum Spiritualium &amp; Tempora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lium
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:63248:41"/>conceſſerunt,</hi> &amp;c. And in the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denture it ſelf, which is Engliſh <hi>We your poor Commons by the aſſent of all the Lords Spiritual and Temporal in this Parlament aſſembled grant,</hi> &amp;c. And in the ſame Parliament two other Subſidies are granted in the ſame form, one for a Fifteenth and a Tenth, the other for 37000 <abbr>
                  <hi>l.</hi>
               </abbr> And it may be boldly affirmed, that ever ſince there hath been a Houſe of Commons, not one Subſidy hath ever been granted by them alone without the Lords.</p>
            <p>But what he means by his Preſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent of <hi>Ireland,</hi> 15 <hi>H.</hi> 7. we under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand not. For how can it ſignifie any thing as to the Parliament of <hi>England,</hi> to be any rule to it, or evidence of it, or to hold any proportion with it, be it never ſo much ſuch as they would have it? But then what will be ſaid, if it be found to be nothing ſo? For there is awide difference betwixt ſaying, <hi>The Commons give a Subſidy,</hi> and ſaying, <hi>That at the prayer of the Commons it is granted and enacted by authority of Parliament, that a Subſidy be given.</hi> And by that form of Expreſſion they
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:63248:42"/>can no more be ſaid to be the ſole givers of a Subſidy, than to be the ſole makers of all the other Acts of Parliament in <hi>Ireland,</hi> that were then made, for they all run in the ſame ſtile, <hi>c.</hi> 16. <hi>Prayen the Commons that it be enacted this preſent Parliament that every Lord ſhall appear in his Parliament Robes.</hi> And <hi>c</hi> 17. <hi>Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en the Commons that it be enacted, That there be no Peace nor War made in the Land without the Lieutenants or the Deputies licenſe.</hi> So <hi>c.</hi> 20. <hi>Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en the Commons that it be enacted, that no perſons uſe theſe words, Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mabo, Butlerabo</hi> (words it ſeems which were uſed when they Robbed and Plundered). And all the other Acts of Parliament run ſo, yet ſure no bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy can think, it was only their Houſe of Commons that made thoſe Laws, but ſuch was then the form and ſtile in the making of all their Laws.</p>
            <p>All the reſt of the Preſidents cited by him, in the times of <hi>H.</hi> 8. <hi>E.</hi> 6. Qu. <hi>M.</hi> Qu. <hi>Eliz. Car.</hi> 1. and <hi>Car.</hi> 2. are by his own confeſſion ſtill with the aſſent of the Lords, and how little
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:63248:42"/>that makes for his purpoſe, needs not that any more be ſaid to it.</p>
            <p>As for that of 1 Qu. <hi>Eliz.</hi> when the Lords did reſpite the payment of the Subſidy for ſome time as to <hi>Che<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhire</hi> and <hi>Wales,</hi> (which is an undeni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able Preſident of their eaſing the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject upon occaſion) it doth not at all alter the Caſe, what was ſaid of their addreſs to the Queene, and of the Entry in the Journall Booke of her pleaſure ſignified for it: For that was but a civill reſpect to her, that they would not diminiſh her profit in any thing without acquainting her with it, and the having her leave: But ſtill it was done by their authority, and it was an Act of that Houſe: And the power to doe it was then well knowne, as appears by the Petition of all the Inhabitants of <hi>Wales</hi> and <hi>Cheſhire,</hi> preſented to the Lords for that purpoſe by the hands of the Knights and Burgeſſes ſerving for them in the Houſe of Commons that Parliament, nor would they elſe have Petitioned the Lords, nor durſt the Members of the Houſe of Gommons
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:63248:43"/>that repreſented them in that Houſe have delivered it.</p>
            <p>But admit there were no Preſidents of the Lords giving eaſe to the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, and making, abatements of a Change laide by the Houſe of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons, whether upon Merchandize or any thing elſe, and that noe complaint had ever beene, and ſo no alteration or amendment ever made: It doth not follow, that therefore they have not power to doe it, when there is cauſe for it, and that there are com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaints of Exceſſe or Inequality in a Tax, as now there were complaints ſufficient by all ſorts of People, who dealt in thoſe Commodities upon which the Impoſitions had beene laide, Planters, Merchants and Tradeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men. Therefore the Lords ſay, they inſiſt and rely more upon the Ratio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nality, and intruth Neceſſity of the thing for the good of the King and Kingdome, then upon any Preſident that can be for it: And yet Preſidents wee ſee there are ſeveral ones; How<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever, they ſay it were enough for their juſtification, if there be none
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:63248:43"/>againſt it, and there could be but of one of theſe two kinds, either that the Lords have of themſelves diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claimed ſuch a power, or that it hath beene denyed them when they have claimed it, and whoever ſheweth one of either, <hi>Erit mihi magnus Apollo.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By what hath beene ſaid, appears, how little reaſon the Manager had to brag of a 300 years uninterrupted poſſeſſion of this Priviledge claimed by the Houſe of Commons to be the ſole abſolute and uncontrouled Taxers of the People, not only in their Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merce and Trading; but in all Money matters: For to that large extent hath he now ſtretched the queſtion, which he narrowed in the beginning: And ſo the Lords muſt not in any caſe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpoſe, to give relief and eaſe to the People, if there be never ſo much cauſe: But either they muſt not joyne to give any Aide to the King, and ſo the King be unſupplied, or they muſt be made Inſtruments againſt their Judgements, and againſt their certaine knowledge, to oppreſs the People, which all unequal Taxes doe; So if
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:63248:44"/>they deny paſſage to the Bill, the King ſuffers; If they give it paſſage, and make it a Law, it wrings the People. Yet this muſt be, or elſe ſaith the Manager, <hi>The Lords doe what in them lyes to put an end to all further Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſactions betweene the Houſes in matter of Money,</hi> he might as well have ſaid in all matters of Parliament, for that muſt be the conſequence: And he is deſired to conſider where the fault will lye, and who demands unreaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable things, ſuch as <hi>Nahaſh</hi> did of the men of <hi>Jabeſh Gilead</hi> to thruſt out their right eyes: So would this even thruſt out one of the eyes of the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, make the Houſe of Lords to be nothing, an inſignificant thing, of no uſe, no advantage to the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome: Therefore it is hoped the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration will be taken on the other ſide, though an <hi>Item</hi> be given to the Lords to conſider of it; implying, that ſince, <hi>It may put an end to all tranſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions betweene the Houſes in matter of Money,</hi> the Lords ſhould apprehend, that the Houſe of Commons might perhaps admit of no more Conferen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:63248:44"/>in any buſineſs of this nature, but would doe it of themſelves, without communicating it to them, who then could not ſo much as take notice, that ſuch a thing was in agitation. But there are Preſidents, that the Lords have of themſelves uncalled, taken notice of, and interpoſed in debates of that nature, which have beene in the Houſe of Commons; And when conteſts and differences have riſen there, and that the Houſe of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons could not come to any reſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion among themſelves, they have compoſed and ſetled the buſineſs, and have directed and appointed what ſhould be done. As 3 <hi>H.</hi> 6. The Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons with the Lords aſſent had grant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed a Subſidy of 33 <hi>s.</hi> 4 <hi>d.</hi> upon every Sack of Wool, as much upon every 240 Woolfells, 3 <hi>s.</hi> upon a Tun of Wine, and upon all other Merchan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dize 12 <hi>d.</hi> in the pound, under the condition (ſaith the Record) That every Merchant ſtranger coming into the Kingdome ſhould within 15 dayes be under Hooſt, and within 40 dayes after his being ſo under Hooſt, ſhould
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:63248:45"/>ſell off all his Merchandize, and what after that remained unſold, ſhould be forfeited to the King; and likewiſe ſhould pay forty three ſhillings four pence (that was 10 <hi>s.</hi> more than the <hi>Engliſh</hi>) upon every Sack of Wool, and every 240 Woolfells: And if theſe conditions were not obſerved, the whole grant of Tunnage and Poundage of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Merchant to be void and of no value: Theſe Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions it ſeems were not obſerved; and great ſtir there was about it in the Houſe of Commons the next Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, which was 4 <hi>H.</hi> 6. as appears by the Record, which ſaith thus, <hi>Item pro eo qd. inter Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>es Parlamenti prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicti diverſae opiniones de &amp; ſuper conceſſione &amp; levatione Subſidii Tona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gii &amp; Pondagii Domino Regi in Parla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mento ſuo ultimo tento conceſſi motae fuerunt ut dicebatur &amp; ſubortae, viſa tandem &amp; diligenter examinata for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma conceſſionis Subſidii praedicti in praeſenti Parlamento, habita quo<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> inde Juſticiar. &amp; aliorum Legis peri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torum deliberatione matura, conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratum fuit &amp; plenius declaratum
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:63248:45"/>per magnificum Principem Ducem Bed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eord Commiſſarium Domini Regis ac faeteros Dominos Spirituales &amp; Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porales in eodem praeſenti Parlamento exiſtentes, qd. Subſidium praedictum ad opus praefati Domini Regis omnino eſſet ſolvendum &amp; levandum, aliqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus conditionibus in conceſſione ejuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dem Subſidii contentis in aliquo non obſtantibus.</hi> The Lords eaſed the Merchants ſtrangers, and yet the Houſe of Commons was not angry at it, nor did they threaten them, that they would have no more to doe with them, and that there ſhould be no further tranſactions between the Hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes in matter of Money; but <hi>Tempora mutantur,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>And ſo we have gone through the Preſidents for the matter of Subſidies, which were cited at the Conference by him that managed it for the Houſe of Commons. Let us now ſee what will be offered by him in point of Reaſon, in anſwer unto their Lordſhips reaſons, He begins with a terrifying general Poſition, which he puts in the front, as a Caveat to their Lordſhips,
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:63248:46"/>
               <hi>That it is a very unſafe thing in any ſetled Government to argue the Reaſons of the Fundamental Conſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutions: for that</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>can tend to nothing that is profitable to the whole.</hi> As if their Lordſhips were now unravelling a ſetled Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, whereas their Lordſhips are now argueing againſt the unſetling of an ancient Government, and the ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting up of a new one, altogether un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowne to our Anceſtors, which is, To have the Trade and the Treaſure, and the ſtrength of the Kingdome to be wholly in the hands, and in the abſolute diſpoſe of one of the Houſes of Parliament, be it either of them. This certainly would be the unſafety of the Kingdome, and the arguing againſt it, and oppoſing it, is for the ſafety of the Kingdome.</p>
            <p>Then he brings in (if one may ſay ſo) a little improperly the Queſtion of Judicature, a point formerly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troverted by the Houſe of Commons, in which he will have no better luck, than in all the reſt: miſtaking or miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citing his Preſidents. He firſt brings
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:63248:46"/>in the Booke Caſe of 22 <hi>E.</hi> 3. to ſhew, that ſometimes it was not in the whole Houſe of Lords, but ſuch as the King would pleaſe to appoint, to exerciſe that Power. The Caſe is this, A Judgement had beene given in the Kings Bench for the King againſt <hi>Ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mond Hadelow</hi> and his Wife, they bring a Writ of Error in Parliament; <hi>Sur que le Roy aſſigne certein Countz et Barons et aueſ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> eux les Juſtices, &amp;c. de terminer le dit beſoignes:</hi> The King appointed certaine Earls and Barons with the Judges to end the matter: But this might be a Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mittee appointed by the Houſe and Judges to attend it, (which were re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gular enough) and yet might be ſaid to be done by the King, as in all their Judicial proceedings, things were ſaid ſtill to be done by the King, if the King were preſent, as ſometimes he was, when ſuch matters were in agi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, and that the Houſe acted as a Court of Juſtice, and not in its Legiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lative capacity. And the rather it ſeems to have then beene ſo, by way of Committee, becauſe the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:63248:47"/>ending, the Booke ſaith, they could proceed no further, and the buſineſs fell to the ground, whereas if they had beene Referrees appointed by the King their authority had beene the ſame after the Parliament as during the Parliament.</p>
            <p>As to the next quotation of the Parliament Roll 25 <hi>E.</hi> 3. n. 4. it muſt be ſome miſtake, for nothing is to be found there relating in any ſort to the matter in hand: but n. 10. there is ſomething to this purpoſe, which per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps the Manager meant, though if duely conſidered it makes againſt him. The Caſe is, That the King cauſed to be brought into Parliament the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord of the proceeding againſt Sir <hi>Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liam Thorp</hi> Chief Juſtice, <hi>Et le ſit lire ouuertement deuaunt les Grauntz du Parlement,</hi> and cauſed it to be read openly before the Lords, to have their advice upon it, who Judged it to be rightly and duely made, and appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved of the Judgement given againſt him, becauſe he had bound himſelf by Oath to undergoe ſuch puniſhment, if he did contrary to what he had
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:63248:47"/>ſworne, which was not to take any bribes: <hi>Et ſur ceo y fut accorde par les Grauntz de meſme le Parlement; que ſi nul tiel cas aui gne dejorenauant que noſtre Seigneur le Roy preigne luy des Grauntz que lui plerra et per lour bon auis fait outre ceo<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> pleiſe a ſa Royale Seigneurie.</hi> The Lords doe agree, that if any ſuch caſe happen afterwards, the King may take ſuch of his Lords as he pleaſe, and by their advice further doe what ſeems good unto him. Is there any thing here that doth derogate from the Lords power of Judicature? or rather can any thing be more in affirmance of it. One who out of Parliament had beene tryed and condemned by a Special Commiſſion, the King the next Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament brings the whole buſineſs be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Lords before any Execution be of that Judgement, to have their Judgement upon that Judgement: they confirm it, and further (as it ſeems by the Record) give the King power in the like Caſe to call what Lords he thinks good, and by their advice to determine it. (which is to
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:63248:48"/>be ſuppoſed meant by them, if the Caſe happen out of Parliament.) And certainly there cannot be a ſtronger argument for the Judicature of the Houſe of Peers in Parliament.</p>
            <p>Then he brings Preſidents to ſhew, that by the Kings good pleaſure, the Commons have beene let into a ſhare of the Judicature, His firſt is the 42 <hi>E.</hi> 3. n. 20, 21. The buſineſs was this, The King the laſt day of the Parliament, invited all the Lords and <hi>Pluſours des Comunes,</hi> many of the Commons to dinner, <hi>Et aprez manger vindrent les Prelats Counts Barons et aſcuns des Communes en la dite Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bre blanche,</hi> And after they had eaten, the Prelates, Earls, Barons, and ſome of the Commons (probably not all they that had dined there, for the Record is <hi>Aſcuns</hi>) went into the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid Chamber blanche, (which is now the Court of Requeſts, where the Houſe of Lords then ſate, as the Commons <hi>En la petite ſale,</hi> (the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord ſaith) in the little Hall) and thither was brought Monſieur <hi>John de la Lee,</hi> and tryed for ſeveral Crimes
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:63248:48"/>laid to his charge, the Articles read by the Chief Juſtice <hi>Robert de Thorp Del commandement des Seigneurs illoeques aſſemblez,</hi> by the Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Lords who were there aſſembled; ſo likewiſe the Record ſaith that his anſwer, <hi>Fuſt auis aux Seigneurs non reſonable,</hi> ſeemed to the Lords not to be reaſonable. And then n. 22. the Record ſaith further, that he was, <hi>Mis a reaſon deuant les Seigneurs,</hi> tryed by the Lords upon an other point. The Concluſion was, That he was ſent to the Tower, and made Fine and Ranſome to the King; But all was done by the Lords, who ſate there as a Houſe in their Judica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, the few Commoners who were preſent, being but ſo many private perſons, and lookers on, and not the leaſt colour of their bearing any part in the Judicature.</p>
            <p>As to his next quotation of 31 <hi>H.</hi> 6. n. 10. nothing can be ſaid: it muſt be miſtaken. For in that Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, wee find nothing of this na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture. The Complaint of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons to the Houſe of Lords for their
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:63248:49"/>Speaker being impriſoned, and their deſire to have him releaſed, which would not be granted, was indeed that Parliament.</p>
            <p>But to <hi>Hugh Brice</hi>'s Caſe, 8 <hi>E.</hi> 4. a clear anſwer may be given, That what was therein done, was by Act of Parliament, in a Legiſlative way. The Commons Petitioning in theſe words, <hi>Pleaſe it therefore your Highneſs by the Advice and Aſſent of the Lords Spiritual and Temporal in this Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment aſſembled, and by authority of the ſame, to aſſign, name and appoint the full reverend Fader in God</hi> Tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas <hi>Cardinal Arch-Biſhop of</hi> Canter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bury, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Then names ſeveral Lords both Spiritual and Temporal, the three Chief Judges of the three Courts, and ſome of the Houſe of Commons to be the perſons to examine that buſineſs, and heare thoſe complaints againſt <hi>Brice</hi> the Maſter of the Mint, The King's Anſwer is, <hi>Le Roy le voet</hi> with a ſaving to his Prerogative Royal: conceiving it (it ſeems) to be ſome derogation to it, that the Commons ſhould be admitted to any part of
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:63248:49"/>Judicature, though by a ſpecial Law for it. For this was a perfect Act of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, in which the three Eſtates concurred in their Legiſlative capa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>city, which had no affinity with the Judicial Power exerciſed by the Lords in their Houſe, as the higheſt Court of Judicature.</p>
            <p>As for his Preſident of 2 <hi>H.</hi> 5. where he ſaith, It was aſſigned for error in the Houſe of Peers, that the Lords gave Judgement without the aſſent or a Petition of the Commons, It was the Earle of <hi>Salisbury</hi>'s Caſe, to reverſe the Judgement given upon his Father, and it is true indeed, it was aſſigned for an Error, but it is as true, it was not allowed to be one, for his Writ of Error was rejected, and that Judgement was affirmed. And ſtrange it is that he ſhould produce this for a Preſident to prove a Partnerſhip of Judicature in the Commons, being a ſtrong one againſt it: And as well might at any time a Plaintiffs Bill in Chancery be produced for Evidence againſt a Defendant in ſome other ſuite, even when the Bill hath beene diſmiſſed.</p>
            <pb n="96" facs="tcp:63248:50"/>
            <p>And his next Preſident is juſt ſuch an other, to ſhew that the King and Commons alone without the Lords have made Acts of Parliament, for which he quotes 1 <hi>E.</hi> 6. c. 5. It is a Statute againſt conveying Horſes out of <hi>England,</hi> and it is true that in <hi>Pul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton</hi>'s Collections it is ſo Printed, as enacted by the King and Commons, without mention of the Lords. But if the Journal of the Lords Houſe had been conſulted, it would have ſhewed, that the Bill began in their Houſe, was read the firſt time the 1ſt. of <hi>December</hi> upon a <hi>Thurſday.</hi> The ſecond time upon a <hi>Wedneſday</hi> the 7th. The third time upon <hi>Saturday</hi> the 10th. and ſent down to the Houſe of Commons by the Kings Attorney and Sollicitor the 22 <abbr>
                  <hi>d.</hi>
               </abbr> of <hi>December</hi> upon a <hi>Thurſday:</hi> the Houſe of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons ſent it up againe with a Proviſo to be added, which Proviſo was al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed of by the Lords, and the Bill diſpatched the <hi>Saturday</hi> after. It was therefore a foul miſtake to ſay this Bill paſſed without the Lords. And it may be modeſtly ſaid of all his Preſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dents,
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:63248:50"/>both concerning the Legiſlative and the Judicature, that upon better conſideration he will not finde cauſe of great encouragement from them to argue the foundations of either Power in order to that Super-ſtructure which he would reare, whither in diminu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of that Power which is challeng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by the Houſe of Peeres in the Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſlative for Impoſitions, or mainte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance of that which he pretends to for the Houſe of Commons in point of Judicature.</p>
            <p>And now wee come to his particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar Anſwers to the Reaſons given by the Lords. And to ſo much and ſo many of thoſe Anſwers, as ſeeme to containe any thing of weight, and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terial to be replied unto, we ſhall give that Reply that is neceſſary: but as for that which is jocular, and hath ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing of reflection in it, as too much of it hath, onely this ſhall be ſaid, <hi>Auferat oblivio ſi poteſt, ſi non, ſilentium teget:</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To the 1ſt. Reaſon then given by the Lords, which was, <hi>That the happineſs of the Conſtitution, is to have one Houſe to be a Cheek to the
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:63248:51"/>other;</hi> his Anſwer being, <hi>That the Lords having a Negative voice to the whole, is a ſufficient Check to the Houſe of Commons.</hi> It is replyed, That to have a Negative voice is not to be a Check: A Negative voice is one thing, a Check is an other. The King hath a Negative voice to what both Houſes doe, yet he cannot be ſaid to be a Check to the Houſes, The two Houſes have each of them a Negative voice to the Convocation granting Subſidies, yet they cannot be ſaid to be Checks to the Convocation: But each to other in their Legiſlative capacity have both a Check and a Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gative voice, which are different ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations of that Legiſlative Power. For properly to be a Check is to have a truſt repoſed in one to examine the Act of an other; And both are truſted by, and accountable to a third perſon, by whoſe authority, and for whoſe Service both are employed. And he that is the Check, cannot wholy reject what the other hath done, be it an account or any thing elſe, he can onely examine it if it be right; And if any
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:63248:51"/>error be, he can correct it and reforme it, and make it ſuch, as that he who employes them both, may receive no dammage nor prejudice by it. And this is the proper worke of the Houſe of Peeres, as they are a Check to the Houſe of Commons (for they have a Negative voice beſides, which is not now the Queſtion, but onely as they are a Check, and ſo) they are truſted both by the King and People, as well as is the Houſe of Commons: not onely in Money-matters, but in all things elſe, cogniſable by the Parliament. If the Houſe of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons give Money ſo to the King, as the Subject cannot beare it, if out of Trade, ſo as Trade cannot beare it (which is the proper queſtion now) <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> out of the Eſtates of the People, ſo as they are not able to pay it, the King himſelf ſuffers in all this, as well as the People, it will be his dammage, his loſs at the laſt; nay the greateſt damage and loſs will be his at the long run, perhaps immediately; for as the ſaying is, <hi>He that graſpes too much, holds nothing;</hi> ſo if more be given
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:63248:52"/>than can be paide, nothing may be received. A thing which King <hi>James</hi> of bleſſed memory did well under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand; and therefore in the Seſſion of Parliament 7<hi rend="sup">mo.</hi> the 21. of <hi>March,</hi> he called both Houſes to him to <hi>White<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hall</hi> upon occaſion of an Aide then demanded, and there among other things, ſaid this to them, <hi>If you give more than is fit, you abuſe the King and hurt the People; and ſuch a Gift I will never accept, for in ſuch a caſe you might deceive a King in giving your flattering conſent to that, which you know might move the People generally to grudge and murmure at it: And ſo ſhould the King ſind himſelf deceived in his Calcul, and the People likewiſe be grieved in their hearts.</hi> And a little after he added theſe words, <hi>I doe not deſire you ſhould yield to that extreeme in giving more than is ſit, for that were to give me a Purſe with a Knife.</hi> That wiſe King knew the inconvenience of ſtraining that ſtring too much, winding it ſo high as to endanger the cracking. Therefore if
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:63248:52"/>any miſtake have beene (as among the wiſeſt of men there may be) the Lords are there to diſcharge their truſt, and ſo rectifie, ſo mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derate, ſo proportion the payments to the ability of them that are to make thoſe payments, as that they may not be ruined, but be able to diſcharge theſe now, and the like hereafter, when there will be need againe. Which anſwers the ſecond part of what is objected, <hi>That it would be a double Check upon His Majeſties affairs, if he may not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye upon the Quantum, when once his People have given it:</hi> So far from it that it will be an advantage to His Majeſties affairs, when the <hi>Quantum</hi> is made ſuch, as he ſhall be ſure to receive it, and that he may thereby have both the Purſe and the hearts of the People. And as to this particular now in queſtion, the <hi>Quantum</hi> upon the whole matter would not have beene leſs to the King, but much greater at the yeares end: For if Trade be over-burthened once, it ſinks, and yields nothing,
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:63248:53"/>and noe where is the Proverbe more truely verified, <hi>That light gaine makes the heavy Purſe,</hi> than in the returne upon Trade, to make it quick and eaſie, which cannot be, if it be over-charged.</p>
            <p n="2">2dly, As to the Writ of Summons, which the Manager acknowledgeth to be <hi>de quibuſdam arduis,</hi> but that it muſt be underſtood of ſuch things as by courſe of Parliament are pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per to Parliament, (which matter of Money (as he will underſtand it) is not to the Houſe of Lords, elſe, ſaith he, the Commons may aſwel in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>title themſelves to Judicature, for they are alſo called to treate <hi>de qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſdam arduis.</hi> To this is replied, that <hi>Quaedam ardud</hi> comprizeth all that the Parliament takes cogniſance of, which are the great and arduous affairs of the Kingdome, as it is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed, 9 <hi>H.</hi> 4. n. 21, 22. <hi>L'eſtat du Royalme et la remedie a ce beſoigna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble,</hi> whatever concerns the ſtate of the Kingdome, and the neceſſary re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medies to it: In all theſe things both Houſes are equally concerned, and
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:63248:53"/>equally called by the King, to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider and debate them, and to give him their adviſe upon them: And there can be nothing of more im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portance to the ſtate of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, and conſequently more pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per for the care and inſpection of both Houſes, than the ſupply of the King with Moneys neceſſary to ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port the Government, make Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of Ships, Armes, Stores, and all things needfull for the defence of the Kingdome, and to defray all other charges incident to the Crowne. But the exerciſing of a Judicature is clean of another nature, and the proper worke of a Court of Juſtice, which the Houſe of Peeres is natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally by the Fundamental Conſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of it: not that the Parliament is called for that purpoſe, but the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament being called, and met accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the Call, the Houſe of Peeres then becomes a Court of Juſtice, for the exerciſe of a Judicial power in thoſe extraordinary Caſes, which by the Cuſtome and uſage of Parliament are within their cogniſance and
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:63248:54"/>Juriſdiction, and have beene ſo from the beginning, long before there ever was a Houſe of Commons: And therefore the Power of Judicature cannot be within the <hi>Quibuſdam arduis,</hi> of which the Houſe of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons is to treate.</p>
            <p>Then for the third Reaſon, to which was given a Rhetorical anſwer (for there was the Rhetorick.) The Lords had by way of Queſtion propoſed to know, when they had appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priated this Right of Impoſing upon Merchandizes to the Commons in ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſion of themſelves; which well they might, having proved it to have been originally in them, and then it was but reaſon to put the Commons to ſhew when they loſt it, according to that knowne Maxime, <hi>Quod noſtrum eſt, ſine facto ſeu defectu noſtro amitti, ſen in alienum transferri non poteſt.</hi> This was no Rhetorical Queſtion, but the Anſwer was Rhetorical, to give the Lords a <hi>Quid pro Quo,</hi> with an other Queſtion, and ask, <hi>Where was the Record by which the Commons ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>itted, that Judicature ſhould be ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>propriated
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:63248:54"/>to the Lords in excluſion of themſelves: And that upon the back of that Record their Lordſhips would find the other endorſed.</hi> This is a fine inſinuation, that all is but a fiction of their Lordſhips Title to the ſole Judi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cature, but it will be made out, that they can ſhew a good title to it, not onely of Cuſtome and Preſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, from the very beginning of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liaments, before there was a Houſe of Commons, but a good Law made in the Caſe, &amp; the ſtrongeſt kind of Law, that is to ſay, to declare a right, (not to conſtitute it) for that Right had beene acknowledged and practiſed time out of mind, beyond all Record; And this was 1 <hi>H.</hi> 4. The Commons then come up, and repreſent to the King and Lords, <hi>Que comme les Juge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mens appartiennent ſeulement an Roi et as Seigneurs et nient as Cöes, &amp;c.</hi> That as Judgements belong onely to the King and Lords, and not to the Commons, ſo they pray that noe Entry may be made in Parliament to make them parties now or <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>ter to any Judgement given or to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven:
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:63248:55"/>To which was anſwered, <hi>That the Commons were but Petitioners, and that the King and Lords have at all times had, and are to have the right of Judicature in Parliament, which Order the King will have to be obſerved in all future times.</hi> This was a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect Law, and the ſame formality uſed to it, as went to the making of all the Laws of thoſe times: And the Record of this is upon the Roll in the Tower, and yet noe endorſing upon it of the other Record, to make the Commons the ſole unlimitted and uncontroula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble diſpoſers of the Peoples Money: For that indeed is onely to be found upon the back ſide of the Salique Law, as the Gentleman ſaid of a thing that was noe where to be found, from whom this whole conceit is borrowed.</p>
            <p>To the 4th of the Lords ſaying, That <hi>by the ſame reaſon of deny<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing them Power to abate, they may deny them Power to reject the whole, and at laſt take away their Negative voice;</hi> and the Managers anſwering this with inſtances of the
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:63248:55"/>King's Negative voice to Bills, and that of the two Houſes to the King's Pardon, and the Clergies Subſidy, who can each of them reject the whole, yet cannot alter any part, and their Negative voices not be in dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger for all that; To all which noe more need be replyed, than what hath beene already ſaid, That in all things of which the Houſes can take cogniſance, they have a Deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berative voice, as well as a Negative, and by the ſame reaſon that the one is taken away, the other may be ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken away likewiſe. But of theſe things they have noe cogniſance, not of the Pardon, becauſe it is the King's free gift; and as for the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidy of the Clergy, the Clergy could tell them, 4 <hi>R.</hi> 2. n. 13, 14. when the Houſe of Commons had offered to grant an Aide, if the Clergy would pay a third part of it, who held a third part of the Realme; The Clergy an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered, they were not to grant Aides by Parliament, and therefore willed the Commons to doe their duties, and they would doe theirs.</p>
            <pb n="108" facs="tcp:63248:56"/>
            <p>As to the 5th. where the Lords ſaid, <hi>That the Commons might allow them the ſame Priviledge of altering and amending of Bills of Money, that they doe the Commoas in Bills of Judicature,</hi> The Manager will take it for an offer; as if the Lords would compound upon terms. But he is miſtaken. The Lords very well know, that it is not Parliamentary to make bargaines. They neither deſire to have more Power in either the one or the other, Moneys or Judicature, than doth of right belong unto them, nor will they depart with that which doth. And to that which was ſaid of Forbearing the inſtances, hoping they will reforme: All they will ſay is this, They know not wherein they have done amiſs.</p>
            <p>To the 6th. of the <hi>Ignoble Choice, which the Lords ſay they are put to, of either not ſupplying the King, or conſenting to wayes, which their owne Judgement and the Good of the Government, and of the People will not admit;</hi> to which are made two Objections.
<list>
                  <item>1. That thereby
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:63248:56"/>the Lords make their Judgements the meaſure of the wellfare of the People.</item>
                  <item>2. That by that rule they may as well encreaſe as abate the Taxes.</item>
               </list>
And then he endeavours to retort this upon the Lords, ſaying, <hi>That the ignoble choice is left by it to the King and the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, That ſo ſmall an Aide muſt be demanded by him, and given by them, as not to be capable of diminution, or otherwiſe it muſt be ſubject to the Lords re-examination, whoſe pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portions in the Taxes in compariſon to what the Commonalty pay is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſiderable.</hi> To this will be replyed in the ſame order; 1. That it is moſt agreeable to reaſon, that their Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhips being to act in the concernes of the People, to make Lawes by which a proportion of their Eſtates is to be diſpoſed of for publick uſe, for the neceſſities of the King and Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and conſequently for the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation of the whole, they ſhould apply the beſt of their Judgements to do it ſo, as it may beſt conſiſt with the wellfare of the People, which
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:63248:57"/>wellfare they muſt ſo meaſure, and ſo guide, and regulate their determina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions by it, that what they doe may not be hurtful to it, Therefore they may without vanity grant what is ſaid, That they doe in that ſenſe make their Judgments the meaſure of the wellfare of the Commons of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land.</hi> To his ſecond objection their Lordſhips ſay (as before) that it is out of the Caſe, they pretend not to a Power of encreaſing Taxes. And then for matter of payment, the Houſe of Lords indeed will not compare with the whole Commo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nalty (nor doe they in their Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liamentary capacity, looke upon the Commonalty of <hi>England</hi> in a diſtinct notion from themſelves, conceiving themſelves truſted for them and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſted in their concernments, as much as any Houſe of Commons,) but they ſay they pay their pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portion as well as the Houſe of Commons. And which of the Hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes payes moſt is not material, both certainly paying what is their due to pay.</p>
            <pb n="111" facs="tcp:63248:57"/>
            <p>As to the 7th concerning poſitive Aſſertions; It is true, they have on both ſides beene poſitive enough, but which hath better maintained their Aſſertions, and made them good, and which hath better proved three hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred years uſage, let neither party be Judge, but the indifferent looker on, who many times ſees more than the Gameſters.</p>
            <p>As to what was ſaid in Anſwer to the 8th and 9th of the Lords Reaſons, it not ſignifying any thing as to the deciſion of the matter in queſtion, but rather ſomething ſavouring of harſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and of unkindneſs, as, <hi>That this Houſe of Commons ſtands in no need of their Lordſhips recommendation, of it ſelf deſerving ſo well both of King and People,</hi> and then conclud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing with an <hi>Item</hi> to the Lords, <hi>To follow the wiſdome of their Anceſtors,</hi> as implying they did not ſo: Expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions fitter to be forgotten, than to be replyed unto: All this therefore ſhall be paſt over with Silence, in purſuance of <hi>Solomon</hi>'s counſel, <hi>To leave off Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention before it be meddled with.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="112" facs="tcp:63248:58"/>
            <p>The ſumme of all is, That the Lords are not at all convinced with either the Arguments or Preſidents brought by the Houſe of Commons, to believe, that ever they had, or that it is agreeable to Reaſon, or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſting with the Nature of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and the general good of the Kingdome, that they ſhould have ſuch a Fundamental Right, as they pretend to, in Bills of Rates and Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitions upon Merchandize, as to the Matter, Meaſure and Time (for thoſe are their words) They to be the ſole Arbiters for the laying on of what Rates and Impoſitions they think good in thoſe three reſpects; And the Houſe of Peers not to intermeddle, nor have Power to make any altera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and abatement in them, when once reſolved by the Houſe of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons, be there never ſo much reaſon, nay a neceſſity ſo to doe. This can no wayes be agreed to. And the Lords do ſay, as to what concernes their Rights and Priviledges, firſt in Generall, That they pretend not to be the beginners of any Charge to
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:63248:58"/>be laide upon the Eſtates of the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject; nor to encreaſe and augment any, that is already laide by the Houſe of Commons. This they conceive to be againſt the intendment of the Law 9 <hi>H.</hi> 4. and the practice of Parliament ever ſince. But they ſay in the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond place as to this Particular now in Queſtion of Tunnage and Poun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dage, That they do challenge a Right and Liberty to have the uſe of their Reaſon, when ſuch Bills come to them from the Houſe of Commons, to judge of the equality of the Rates impoſed, to moderate and reduce them to a due proportion, if they find any too high, and to receive the complaints and information of Merchants and Perſons concerned, or of any other, who is experienced in Trade, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by to regulate their Proceedings in the conſideration of thoſe Bills, that they may ſo frame and model them, before they give their Aſſent unto them, as to be ſure they may be ſuch, as Trade ſhall not ſuffer, and yet the King be ſupplyed, and thoſe great Ends complied with for the generall
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:63248:59"/>Good and Benefit of the Kingdome, for which thoſe Subſidies are given. This the Lords doe affirme to be the undoubted Right and Priviledge of the Houſe of Peeres, and an Eſſential part of that Power and Authority, which the Conſtitution of this Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, and the Cuſtome and uſage of Parliament hath lodged there for the Good of the Nation, and which hath ſo continued, and beene enjoyed and exerciſed by them for that End, from the very beginning both of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liaments and Government.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="errata">
            <head>ERRATA.</head>
            <p>PAg. 87. li. 1. for <hi>Bedcord</hi> reade <hi>Bedfordiae,</hi> and li. 3. for <hi>ſaeteros,</hi> reade <hi>caeleros.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:63248:59"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
